<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three homilies upon these three sentences folowing Psal. 55.22. Cast thy burthen vpon the Lord.  Iohn 14.27. My peace I giue vnto you. Luk.10.42. One thing is necessarie. Composed by Philip Mornay, lord of Plessis-Marly.</title>
            <title>Trois homélies. English.</title>
            <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100071</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835923</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1281:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three homilies upon these three sentences folowing Psal. 55.22. Cast thy burthen vpon the Lord.  Iohn 14.27. My peace I giue vnto you. Luk.10.42. One thing is necessarie. Composed by Philip Mornay, lord of Plessis-Marly.</title>
                  <title>Trois homélies. English.</title>
                  <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly, 1549-1623.</author>
                  <author>Ratcliffe, Anthony, fl. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 177, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nathanael Newberry, and are to be sold in Popes-head alley at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Anthony Ratcliffe, of: Mornay, Philippe de. Trois homélies sur ces trois mots: Rejette ta charge sur l'Eternel..</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: A.R., i.e. Anthony Ratcliffe.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of I6.</note>
                  <note>A translation of the original French.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B-H¹²  I⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE HOMILIES Vpon theſe three <hi>ſentences following.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 55.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cast thy burthen vpon the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 14.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My peace I giue vnto you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVK. 10.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>One thing is neceſſarie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Compoſed by <hi>Philip Mornay,</hi> Lord of <hi>Pleſsis Marly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold in Popes-head alley at the ſigne of the Starre. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull and his very loving Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Dorothie Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie,</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> All increaſe of true happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Siſters, ſeing it hath pleaſed God to vnite vs together by moſt neere and ſtrict bands of amity, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe of nature and grace, I haue often beene
<pb facs="tcp:156:3"/>proiecting with my ſelfe which way I might (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my departure out of this world) leaue with each of you ſome expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of that loue, which in regard of both theſe bands, I finde my ſelfe obliged vnto you in. Wherevpon it being my hap during this late and great Viſitation (never to be forgotten) to light vpon a ſubiect, well ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to theſe troublous times, <hi>viz.</hi> theſe 3. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes enſuing, written by a Noble and Iudicious perſonage, in his owne natiue Language: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb facs="tcp:156:3"/>out of that little inſight I had thereinto; by reaſon of my trauels in my yonger yeares, to ſet vpon the tranſlation thereof; time and leiſure ſerving me ſo fitly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And the rather, leaſt with the vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant, I might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be taxed in mine own conſcience, either of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp in a Napkin,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.20 Mat. 25.25.</note> or burying in the earth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this one talent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto my truſt. Now howſoever ſome may here not vntruely obiect, that moe Tracts in this kinde haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:156:4"/>bin brought to light, then are either carefully read, or of the Readers kindly reſpected, yet wel weighing the worth of the points herein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, it ſeemed to mee, that I could not without ſome wrong done to my ſelfe &amp; others, withhold them any longer from the publicke view. For what burdened ſoule, would not gladly accept of caſe? What trembling heart would not reioyce to find peace? And who is he or ſhee, whoſe heart &amp; head being diſtracted &amp; cumbred about many
<pb facs="tcp:156:4"/>carking cares, would not willingly light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that one thing, which being obtained, would breed in them a world of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment? So that vpon the point, theſe 3. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes carefully read, dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and well practiſed, may in ſome caſes proue more beneficiall; then to be left by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, thouſands of gold &amp; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Now as I am bold to publiſh them (my good ſiſters) to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, vnder each of your names &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tronage, ſo is it my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo to bequeath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vnto you, not as a
<pb facs="tcp:156:5"/>worldly, but as a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al legacy, the fruit wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my hope is ſhall abide with you forever. Let me intreate you all then, my deare ſiſters, with good <hi>Mary</hi> to chuſe the better part, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> as Chriſt ſayth, <hi>ſhall never be taken from you,</hi> leſt being overmuch buſied about the things of this life, you ſhould ſeeme to come ſhort of the heavenly: as it is to be feared too many haue already done, doe, &amp; will doe, till they repent the ſame at leiſure. <hi>For what will it profit vs, to gain the whole world, and to loſe
<pb facs="tcp:156:5"/>our owne ſoules; or what can wee giue in exchange for our ſoules?</hi> Mat. 16.26. But beloved Siſters, I am perſwaded better things of you, &amp; ſuch as accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſalvation, though I thus ſpeake. Wherefore accept in loue, what is here preſented vnto you, from a loving heart: and ceaſe not I pray you, to pray for him, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires from the heart, ever to reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Brother, <hi>A. R.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>Ianuary 5. 1625.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> thou haſt heere by the good provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, and not without the faithfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours of a very good friend, a faire opportunitie offred thee to read and read again, if thou be pleaſed, theſe three <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> of the thrice renowned <hi>Philip Mornay,</hi> Lord of <hi>Pleſſis:</hi> who in commenting vpon the holy Scriptures,<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth rather to reſemble <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156:6"/>the divine Evangeliſt, then a peere of that Land where he did reſide. His la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours herein though ſhort, yet ſhalt thou finde them pious, pithy, learned, and ſweete. For here <hi>1.</hi> thou maiſt learne on whom to caſt the burden of thy ordinary and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tryals. <hi>2.</hi> In all outward and inward perturbations, where to finde true peace. <hi>3.</hi> In all thy worldly encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, how to pitch vpon that one thing, which in truth is better then all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever beſides. So as had not my friend and my ſelfe by often viewing and reviewing them over (in theſe late dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dayes) eſteemed, that thy gaine inreading of them would plentifully haue anſwered the
<pb facs="tcp:156:7"/>paine, thou hadſt not I dare aſſure thee in ſo great plentie and varietie of good Bookes at this time, had ſo free an vſe of this; being penned as it was in another Language. Accept it then <hi>Good Reader,</hi> as a pledge of our Loues to thee; as alſo of our earneſt wiſhes, that thou maiſt daily profit in the knowledge of theſe and the like ſacred and divine truthes, to the glory of God, and thine owne eternall good, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt,</hi> C. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156:7"/>
            <head>A HOMELIE Vpon theſe words of DAVID;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Caſt thy Burthen vpon the <hi>LORD,</hi> and he will nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thee,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 55.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>AVID much experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in bearing Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out his ſoule in a moſt bitter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint before God.<note place="margin">ſal. 55.</note> 
               <hi>I grieue,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and am much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156:8"/>becauſe of the voice of the enemie.</hi> But what voice? <hi>They caſt iniquitie vpon mee;</hi> vpon mee poore Innocent, all iniquitie, all manner of Crimes; <hi>And for the furious hatred which they beare mee.</hi> And what Enemie was it? He with whom I was ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, <hi>that we communicated our ſecrets tegether, wee went together into the houſe of God.</hi> And in this caſe what could be more ſayd? When, from whence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ſhould come, thence ariſeth griefe: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſembles he the depth of his anguiſh: <hi>My heart is ſore pained within me. And I ſayd who ſhall giue mee the wings of a Doue that I may flie away?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, now ready to leaue all;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>This affliction aboue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being beyond the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſolation of man. But as ſoone as he was come againe vnto himſelfe, nay rather going out of himſelfe, he redoubles his courage; <hi>I will cry vnto God, and the Lord will deliver me;</hi> if at the firſt he vnderſtand me not, nor anſwere me, I will not recoyle.<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.17.</note> 
               <hi>Evening and morning, and at noone day will I cry aloud, and he will he are my voice.</hi> I will knocke, and that ſo often, and hard at his gate, that he will open vnto mee. Such importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is pleaſing vnto him. Then he giues vs a leſſon; In like care; from whom can we better take it? or vp on better proofe? Verſ. 22.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156:9"/>
               <hi>Caſt thy burthen,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, and he will nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thee.</hi> Art thou a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and overwhelmed with adverſitie, or toyled vnder thy Calling, powre out thy heart vnto the Lord; roule thy ſelfe even vpon him, take him for thy pledge, &amp; doubt not, but as he is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally good and faithfull in his promiſes; ſo he will take thy burthen vpon himſelfe, and comfort thee; In the ſame ſence as he ſaith elſe where. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Stay thy ſelfe vpon the Lord, commit thy way vnto him, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe;</hi> quiet the diſquiemes of thy ſoule; and commit thy ſelfe to his direction; the which S. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo teacheth vs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156:9"/>together with him. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. verſes. <hi>Humble your ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time, caſting all your care vpon him, for he careth for you.</hi> And ſeeing it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him to take the care vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, who hath all times in his hands, let vs not feare, that he will let the time ſlip. Should I caſt my burthen vpon the Lord, may ſome ſay; Is it not over much boldneſſe, were it vpon a brother? Shall the ſervant preſume to lay his burthen vpon his Lord, the Creature vpon his Creator? A crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? nay which is worſe; burthened with vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, with rebellion, and hatefull ſinnes, can this be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156:10"/>done without preſumption? or rather without pride? And what doth God more abhorre? But I will helpe thee in this doubt. It were pride indeed, if thou tookeſt this boldnes from thy ſelfe; But he hath given it thee, he hath ordained it for thee; <hi>Call vpon me, and I will heare thee. Call vnto me, and I will runne to helpe thee;</hi> He is thy ſhepheard, and vouchſafeth to call vs his ſheepe, and the ſhepheard carrieth the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon his ſhoulders bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening himſelf with them; ſo farre is he from caſting them off. Of a Iudge, of a Lord, of a Creator, he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy Father, and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; From whence, even <hi>David</hi> comforts himſelfe.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156:10"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Though my father and mother ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, yet the Lord will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther me vp;</hi> yea the Lord himſelfe ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.15.</note> 
               <hi>Though a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould forget her ſucking childe; the ſonne of her wombe, and take no pittie of it, yet will not I forget thee.</hi> That is to ſay, not my Church, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny member thereof; More tender therfore is he towards vs, then any parents towards their Children, or towards thoſe that hang vpon the breaſt of the tendereſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who in the meane time, run as it were vndone at their cry, oppoſing and expoſing themſelues againſt the cruelleſt beaſts, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, they forget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, goe out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156:11"/>to put themſelues in their place. What then ſhall wee not expect from the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Lord towards his children, from his Bowels ever yearning? From this Father, <hi>who ſpared not his owne ſonne,</hi> his onely ſonne, one with himſelfe, <hi>to giue him for vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Rom. 8. &amp; 32. Of that Sonne who being <hi>in the forme of God, equall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, emptied himſelfe; tooke the forme of a ſervant, and humbled himſelfe vnto the death,</hi> even the ſhamefull and curſed death of the Croſſe; and all this, for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; nay rather for ſlaues, malefactors, and accurſed ſinners.</p>
            <p>Well then, <hi>Caſt thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon the Lord.</hi> No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156:11"/>will take it vpon him, vpon no other canſt thou lay it. But what burthen? He ſaith <hi>thy burthen,</hi> not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very burthen; but <hi>thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</hi> Thine owne burthen; not that which thou impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vpon thy ſelfe, at thine owne will, or doeſt raſhly thruſt thy ſelfe into. Know therefore, if thou be a childe of his family, that thou art in a houſe of order; That is the burthen which he hath layd vpon thee, who by his Ordinance hath made it thine; But take thou heede alſo, that it be from him; that hath a ſoveraigne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge. By him who doth nothing, but by waight, number, and meaſure; it cannot be but well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156:12"/>and rightly added, if according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy ſtrength, of the ſtrength which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee, that thou ſhouldeſt beare it chearfully, that thou ſhouldeſt goe on ſtill in thy Calling with all thy power: if aboue thy power, it is to make thee feele thine owne infirmitie; and to call for his helpe: let thy weaknes hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee before him, and ſtrengthen thy ſelfe with his grace. For how ever it be, thou canſt not lye long vnder the burthen, for as much as his grace is made perfect in thine infirmitie; thy burden is made his; his ſtrength conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth towards thee, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then when thine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156:12"/>Contrariwiſe, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thou vpon thy ſelfe, any croſſe or affliction; thou art in danger leaſt it be ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee; who hath required theſe things at thy handes? Alſo, if thou vndertakeſt a charge according to thine owne will, and afterwardes falleſt vnder it, take heed it be not obiected vnto thee, <hi>thou ranneſt and I ſent thee not.</hi> Ierem. 23. &amp; 21. thou ſpakeſt, and I put not thoſe wordes into thy mouth. Whereas thoſe, vnto whom God hath give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their charge, he bindeth himſelfe to be their Gardian; Saying, <hi>I will be with thee,</hi> and where he is, what can be wanting? <hi>He is faithfull,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>and will not ſuffer his to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156:13"/>tempted aboue their ſtrength; and giueth an iſſue with the temptation:</hi> with his calling, the efficacie. Onely let vs be aſſured, that wee beare the burthen; that we performe our (or rather indeed his) charge, and let vs not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſay with the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>I am able to doe all things, through Chriſt, who ſtrengtheneth me.</hi> Now this burthen is vſually of two ſorts; either a croſſe, or ſome tribulation laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs by God, or elſe a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wherein he hath ſet vs. And that properly is meant here, but in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and higheſt termes. For,<note place="margin">The burden of trials and temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> as for afflictions, it is certain, that there is nothing that liſteth vp our hearts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156:13"/>more vnto God, which draweth them from the earth, they are the bellowes, that kindle prayer in vs, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, as it were, out of the aſhes, But whileſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues within ſome meaſure, ſo as they ſeeme fitted to our ſtrength, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding within the termes of hope, namely, diſgraces, loſs of goods, ſickneſſes, griefes, baniſhments, and ſuch like. But when diſgrace paſſeth vnto perſecutions without cauſe, the loſſe of goods, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſlander againſt our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſickneſſe into agony, griefe into heart-breaking, baniſhment into proſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the accents of our Complaints change their tune, the complaints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156:14"/>are dried vp; and ſo much the more, if theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills be procured by thoſe who ſhuld wiſh vs well, yea, if when thou art moſt wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, whilſt thou takeſt moſt paynes to doe well; And ſo much the more, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth thy perſon, thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, the houſe of God, his Church, (the apple of his eye) Becauſe certainely it ſeemes vnto vs; that God hath loſt his rule, that he remembers not any more what fleſh and bloud is; but rather hath an eye to the minde of man, winding it vp vnto the higheſt pitch; Becauſe it ſeemes, he doth not equally poyſe the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of his juſtice, nor to haue left him any thing but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156:14"/>the ſtring to hold them, when often the wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpereth at the coſts of the godly; the ſlaues, at the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of the children; the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtime,</hi> vnto the ſhame of the <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> reprobate <hi>Saul,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the confuſion of faithfull <hi>David;</hi> He delivers them into their hands, he forſakes them. And therefore we are not to thinke it ſtrange, if the requeſt of <hi>David</hi> paſſeth from a prayer vnto a cry, from a cry vnto a hideous noyſe, from a hideous noyſe vnto a tempeſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. And yet though he caſts not off his burthen: may he not be ſayd to ſhake it off? Hee ſhakes it off, who to deliver himſelfe from affliction, makes a Covenant with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156:15"/>death, and hell; takes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of fleſh &amp; bloud, trades with the world, though it be with loſſe of the glory of God, redeemes himſelfe (he cares not how) from them who perſecute him. <hi>David</hi> doth not ſo, for ſaith he, <hi>death as a tyrant ſhall ſeaſe vpon them.</hi> Pſal. 55.15. But as for me, <hi>I will call vpon the Lord, and he will ſaue mee,</hi> Verſ. 16. Why ſo? Verily becauſe hee knoweth that the Church is Gods buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the faithfull are his true children, and are the only living ſtones ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that amongſt theſe ſtones ſome are hewen, ſome poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for the corner-ſtone, for the maiſter-piece, for <hi>Corinth,</hi> &amp;c. All that come
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156:15"/>vnder his hand, muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the mallet, the chiſlell; and ſo much the rather by how much they are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to a higher place, to wit, to ſtand in the forefront of the building. Seeſt thou any exempted from the hammer, then ſay boldly, they are not fit for his buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Vpon our corner ſtone, he layeth no other, but <hi>choſen &amp; precious.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. yea, himſelfe, to be layd as the head ſtone of the Corner, by what hammers, chiſlells, &amp;c. hath he not paſſed? Namely, calumnies, falſe witneſſes of <hi>Phariſies,</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the cruelties of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, his brethren accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh? Vpon this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156:16"/>ſtone, thinkeſt thou, vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full builder, that there may be ſet any ruffe ones? And thou vntamed member, doſt thou thinke it ſtrange, that to make thee capable thereof, he make thee paſſe vnder the playne, makes thee ſmooth through hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and hewing? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> who had paſſed through ſuch trials, who knew what and how many hewings are needfull for the faithfull, to make them fit for this building, what were the vſes, and benefits of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, which God ſends vs, is not aſhamed to ſay. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 67. that <hi>before he was afflicted he went aſtray,</hi> but now it had brought him backe to his Law; He caſts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156:16"/>not off his burden through deſpaire, but cryes vnto the Lord, and waiteth for his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere; becauſe he aſſures himſelfe, that that ſpirit which cryeth in him <hi>Abba Father,</hi> the ſame eternall ſpirit doubtleſſe will giue him this anſwer; <hi>behold I am with thee,</hi> neerer vnto thee then thy ſelfe; He knowes that the Lord doth willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly draw neere vnto the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hearted &amp; contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. &amp; 18. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights rather to be in the priſon of ſorrow, then in the wedding chamber; in a ſoule withered with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then ſpread out in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe. And in deede ſeldome you ſee ſuch a one powre out his ſoule before
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156:17"/>God, but preſently ſhee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth vp againe her ſelfe in faith and confidence, and her cry is turned into thankſgiving, this ſwound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a ſacrifice of praiſe. Hath <hi>David</hi> ſaid. <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 6. verſ. 3.4.5. &amp; 9. <hi>My bones are vexed, and my ſoule is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed?</hi> By and by alſo followes, <hi>Depart from mee yee workers of iniquitie, the Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping.</hi> And vpon the calumnies of <hi>Cuſſe</hi> the <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamite,</hi> prayeth he. <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2.11.13 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>Lord I draw neere vnto thee, defend mee, that he teare mee not in peeces like a Lyon;</hi> He reſolues with himſelfe, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes 10.11.12. <hi>The Lord is my Buckler, if he turne not,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156:17"/>he will whet his ſword.</hi> There he finds both his weapons offenſiue and defenſiue, <hi>hee ſhall travayle to bring forth wickedneſſe, but ſhall bring forth a lye, his travayle ſhall fall vpon his owne head. I ſaid,</hi> ſaith he elſwhere, <hi>when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſlide,</hi> when I began to be ſwallowed vp with feare, <hi>I am cut off in thy ſight.</hi> Pſal. 31. verſ. 22.23.24. <hi>But thou haſt heard the voice of my ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, when I did cry vnto thee:</hi> glorying therevpon by way of triumph, ſaying, <hi>Loue the Lord all yee his Saints, for he keepeth his faithfull ones; be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and he will ſtrengthen your heart.</hi> And ſo in this place, having felt himſelfe diſcharged of the burthen
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156:18"/>of his griefes, he encourages others; ſaying, <hi>Caſt thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 55. Is he hid in the Deſert of <hi>Ziph,</hi> flying from the fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Saul</hi> his King, being ready to be delivered vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his handes by thoſe of that place? He hath no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſayd,<note place="margin">Pſal. 54.13.</note> 
               <hi>O cruell people; a people that haue not ſet God before their eyes, do even ſeeke my life;</hi> But he preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues, <hi>God is my helpe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> He even burnes with zeale to offer him ſacrifice; <hi>I will,</hi> ſayth he,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſacrifice vnto thee with a free heart, for thou haſt delivered me.</hi> Even thou <hi>haſt</hi> delivered me; He holds his deliverance for accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed he ſees it with his faith, with the eyes of his ſoule;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156:18"/>though a farre off, yet moſt certaine. For the holy Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tells vs, that as <hi>Saul</hi> and his people went purſuing him, a meſſenger met <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaying.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.27.</note> 
               <hi>Make haſt for the Philiſtimes are come into thy Dominions; Saul</hi> preſently breakes off his Chaſe, and behold <hi>David</hi> in an inſtant beyond all expectation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, by meanes of the <hi>Philiſtimes.</hi> And hereunto belongs that of the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. at what time he hid himſelfe in the caue of <hi>Hengedi.</hi> When <hi>Saul</hi> alſo ſent to kill him in his houſe, we ſee him troubled. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9.11. He obſerues their practiſes, their plottes, their watches; he oppoſeth his integritie and his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156:19"/>but with what peace vnto his ſoule? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. ver. 9.12.16. <hi>Lord God, thou wilt laugh at them, and yet Lord ſlay them not, leaſt my people forget it;</hi> He is now more carefull of their life then of his owne. <hi>Lord I will ſing of thy mercy in the morning;</hi> I will not looſe one houre of my ordinary exerciſes. The like examples wee haue alſo in the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> 64.69.140. and many the like, againſt thoſe who eyed him, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched him in his wayes, in his words, &amp; (if they could) even to his very thoughts; But even in the greateſt pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rill, he concludes all in cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine hope of Deliverance; ſaying, <hi>The iuſt ſhall reioyce in the Lord, and ſhall draw
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156:19"/>neere vnto him, and all that are true of heart ſhall be glad and reioyce;</hi> as touching his Iuſtice, which he will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the one, and will doe to the other; <hi>The flouds are riſen vp even vnto my ſoule, I am afflicted and in griefe,</hi> but <hi>thy deliverance ſhall lift mee vp on high,</hi> ſo high, that no waters, no, not a deluge ſhall attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; <hi>I know that the Lord will execute Iuſtice for the afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and howſoever it be, the vpright ſhall dwell before his face.</hi> But ſome prophane perſon may here ſay, is <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> thus confident, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then notwithſtanding lieth ſtill vpon his neeke, he is ſlandered, abuſed, watched, purſued by <hi>Saul,</hi> by his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156:20"/>moſt familiar friends, yea by his owne ſonne; but he is lightened of this his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, comforted in ſoule, becauſe of his liuely faith, which repreſented vnto him the helpe of his God, both certaine and preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his loue by his holy Spirit was powred into his ſoule, becauſe a divine light ſhining vpon it, ſcattered the darkneſſe thereof. And thou Chriſtian, whoſoever thou art, if ever thou haſt called vpon the Lord in the like anguiſh, how often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy burthen (the cauſe of thine anguiſh, of thy griefe) was eaſed; haſt thou notwithſtanding felt thy ſpirit eaſed by thy prayer? God without doubt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156:20"/>his hand inviſibly and inſenſibly vnder thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as it were hidden from thee. The burthen continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet the paine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed; becauſe we haue now two to beare it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſeth God to beare one part of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and that the greateſt part alſo, ſuffering vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double our ſtrength, that he might lend vs his owne.</p>
            <p>For example, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing caſt into the pit by his brethren. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. ver. 27. it was ſome reliefe to be ſolde vnto the <hi>Madianites,</hi> and then vnto <hi>Potipher,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Guard <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.1. his burthen encreaſeth, when the ſlander of his mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtris cauſed him to be caſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156:21"/>into the dungeon; but <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes</hi> addes preſently, that <hi>the Lord was with Ioſeph.</hi> ver. 20. he ſhewed his mercie vpon him; in <hi>giving him favour in the ſight of the Maiſter of the Priſon.</hi> Such favour as made him way to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> even to the ſupplying of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſities of <hi>Iacob</hi> his Father, and all his houſe; yea even to be ruler over <hi>Egypt.</hi> Who now in the meane while would haue beleeved that GOD was with him in priſon? In like manner he ſaith to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> that is, to his Church, &amp; to all the members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.2. <hi>When thou paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee, they ſhall not drowne thee, and when thou goeſt through the fire, it ſhall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156:21"/>not burne thee;</hi> becauſe I will be with thee. Even I, who commandes the elements, who rules over the waters of the Floud. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.10. who makes my Miniſters a flame of fire. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.4. I am with thee, becauſe I haue redeemed thee. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.1. <hi>I haue called thee by name, thou art mine,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent I haue Intereſſe in thy ruine, in thy loſſe. Is God with vs in the fire, and in the water. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.2. if he ſaid it not himſelfe, who durſt beleeue it? And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we ſee it in the waters of the red Sea, which gaue place vnto the Children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> when in the meane while they overwhelmed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſte. Alſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156:22"/>in the three Children in the Furnace,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> being heated more then ordinary, it conſumed them, who caſt them in. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27. but of thoſe that were caſt in, it ſinged not a haire; an Angell ioyning himſelfe vnto them, in the middeſt of the fire, who kept them; <hi>One</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) <hi>like to the Sonne of God.</hi> Theſe things you ſee being performed, both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and viſiblie in them: whence wee may learne, that God who was with his in the middeſt of dangers, out of the which there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared no iſſue, is inviſibly, and no leſſe really with all thoſe, who call vpon him in true faith, he compaſſeth them about with his mercy,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156:22"/>and aſſiſteth them with the preſence of his Angels, yea, of his owne preſence alſo. Whence it is that <hi>David,</hi> hiding himſelfe from the wrath of <hi>Saul</hi> in the Caue, makes his prayer vnto God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4. ſaying, <hi>My ſoule is amongst Lyons, I lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst theſe that are ſet on fire, amongst men whoſe teeth are ſpeares and arrowes;</hi> he aſſures himſelfe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that <hi>God will ſend from heaven, and deliver him;</hi> yea out of this danger; and in this faith he <hi>wakens his tongue,</hi> and all his muſicall inſtruments, to giue him praiſe. This deliverance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto him no leſſe reall, nor leſſe miraculous,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.22.</note> then that of <hi>Daniell</hi> in the denne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156:23"/>of Lyons, in which denne <hi>the Angell of the Lord</hi> did ſhut their mouths; but what if not ſo viſibly; becauſe ſuch miracles, are wrought viſiblie but once, or very rarely; to try our weaknes, as alſo to ſhow that God can doe it, ceaſing not in the meane while inviſibly to continue according to his word &amp; promiſe, which aſſures vs that he will do it. And herein the faithfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, that ſo often as they finde themſelues, amongſt ſuch Lyons, thirſting for their bloud, and hungering for their life, yet can they doe them no hurt? And in ſuch appetite and ſuch fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſeing themſelues a prey, can they doubt of him who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156:23"/>reſtraines them, who muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels them thus inviſiblie? Therefore tell me not here, that wee now ſee no more miracles. We ſee them not indeede, becauſe wee want eyes; for what doe we ſee in effect but miracles? Thou Chriſtian, if the creation of the world, if the vniverſall change of the courſe of the world, by the power of Chriſt, if the death of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Martyrs beleeving the Reſurrection of a God cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, ſo many ages paſt; tell me if ſo ſweete a harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of all and every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thereof, be not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent myracle? In vaine will it be for thee, to ſee the lame to goe, the dumbe to ſpeake, the dead to riſe; Thou ſhalt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156:24"/>alwaies find in thy diſcourſe matter of doubt; they will be vnto thee illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſlights and trickes of Sathan; well then, let vs caſt our burthen vpon the Lord, and let vs the rather conſider of his grace and of his helpe in vs and towards vs. And after we haue ſeriouſly called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, feeling our ſelues in effect either diſcharged of this burden, of this croſſe, which cruſhed vs, or incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to beare it more ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, let vs then boldly ſay; The Lord hath here put to his hand; for from no other but him, could come eaſe of paine, or increaſe of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. Therefore let vs freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, in the healing of our ſtroake; and of this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156:24"/>iſſue of bloud, that vertue is gone out from Chriſt, yea, albeit we haue but touched the hemme of his garment; this touching, this hemme, which is as it were but to giue a body vnto their invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and ſpirituall vertue, thereby to make it vnto vs (fleſh and bloud as we are) not more efficacious, but more ſenſible.</p>
            <p>Well then, if the Lord as in ſome temptations ſeemes to thee that himſelfe takes part againſt thee, and by conſequent thou thinkeſt, that he himſelfe is become the burthen, ſo farre off is it, that thou canſt hope, he ſhould beare thy burthen; vnto whom then ſhouldeſt thou haue recourſe? And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156:25"/>here lyeth the higheſt point of the triall. Take an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God commanded him to offer vp his ſonne, whom he had long time waited for, his <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> his onely ſonne; by that ſo expreſſe a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, vpon ſo ſolemne a promiſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>In Iſaac ſhall thy ſeede be called.</hi> What was here to be done? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely both theſe two, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally obiects of our faith, and of our obedience; the one and the other, being the word of God, but wee will hold vs to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement which bindeth vs,<note place="margin">Note.</note> leaving vnto him the fit time to fulfill his promiſe; And let vs ſay with faithfull <hi>Abraham; The Lord will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:156:25"/>who holds the iſſues of death in his power. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.20. Who can raiſe mee children even out of ſtones, <hi>and can reſtore me this ſonne againe,</hi> if need be, even the ſame and none other <hi>out of the graue;</hi> And yet on this childe depended the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Chriſt, the bleſſed ſeede, the ſalvation of the church? So ought the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to be reſolved to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the voyce of God, with his eyes ſhut, againſt all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, equivocations, &amp; humaine gloſſes; whereof in all perplexities, the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt wiſedome is to be ſilent,<note place="margin">Note.</note> both in God, and to God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.1. How ever it be ſaith the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi> my ſoule is ſilent in God: an higher
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:156:26"/>prayſe we cannot giue vnto him; <hi>To be ſilent,</hi> that is to ſay, he murmures not in himſelfe, replies not againe, but yeelds to his will, and waiteth with patience the iſſue thereof, and ſubmits his whole wiſedome to his providence; This being certainely the higheſt point of faith, to which it is not alwayes given vs to attaine vnto. But if it happen vnto vs, as it did vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his wading through the foord <hi>Iabok,</hi> vpon the point of his meeting with <hi>Eſau,</hi> to wraſtle with God, with our weakneſſe, againſt his promiſes, let vs not truſt ſo much vpon that, that he ſuffers himſelfe to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by vs, vouchſafing to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:156:26"/>condeſcend vnto our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, as to the perpetuall marke he left vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> in his thigh, when he leaues vnto vs the marke, as of his power, ſo of our infirmitie. Of this <hi>power</hi> (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) which is <hi>perfected in our infirmitie.</hi> A healthfull infirmitie, which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to leaue in thoſe that are his, to keepe them in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As in <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> though he bleſſed him, yet he humbled him, that he ſhould not be proud of that bleſſed wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; In like manner in S. <hi>Paul,</hi> notwithſtanding his prayer many times reittera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>leaſt the excellencie of things revealed vnto him, ſhould lift him vp aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> 2 Cor. 12. That we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:156:27"/>ſhould alwayes be forced vnder the heavie burthen of our adverſities, and in our weakneſſe, to call to him for ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Strength, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fayle, ſeeing it is he that promiſeth it, offers it vnto vs, ſo as he even taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be called <hi>our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth,</hi> although ſomedmes he lets vs ſuffer, and groane, being ready to ſinke; but he knowes at what inſtant to helpe vs;<note place="margin">Note.</note> at the halfe blow, as of <hi>Iſaac</hi> vpon the blocke; the more to manifeſt his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; if alſo he lets vs alone in danger, in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; it is alwayes one and the ſame providence, from the ſame art of the Phiſitian proceedeth the inciſion of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:156:27"/>the Patient, and his dyet; both the one and the other, being in his choice, and not in that of the patient. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17. That the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> ſhould be fed by the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, which day by day brought him bread &amp; fleſh, evening and morning, his daily bread; it was the more to make him feele God his fatherly care, and the rather to bring him to commit himſelfe vnto his bountie, then if he ſhould haue ſet before him a ful ſtore houſe of victualls. Vnto the wid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sarepta</hi> alſo, to draw our of her barrell of meale, &amp; her cruſe of oyle, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie it from day to day, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to abundance; it made her the more to feele her
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:156:28"/>want, and in her neceſſitie, the power and bountie of God, and by the one &amp; the other, to keepe her devout, to augment her faith, to heate her zeale; then if at the inſtant, he had given it her in a full barne, &amp; wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler. Becauſe the bleſſings we receiue of God in the whole heape,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, vaniſh away into ſome light thankeſgiving; they are at the firſt but coldly acknowledged to God; and a little while after, they are attributed vnto a friend, and to our good fortune, and to our owne induſtrie; but when they come flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by degrees, ſo as we are conſtrained to waite for them, then they giue vs time
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:156:28"/>to deſire them, to ſigh for them, to taſte them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh them, to fill our ſences, our imagination &amp; memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; And to ſay with <hi>David. Pſal.</hi> 63. <hi>I ſeeke thee at the dawning of the day, my ſoule thirſteth for thee, my fleſh luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth after thee, in a barren and drie Land, where no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is.</hi> Graunt, that he rayne Quailes downe vpon vs, the fleſh being yet between our teeth, wee will be readie to murmure. And therefore the better to flie, to flie I ſay vnto God, we haue need to be kept low; to returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to know his luer, and not to feed vs to our fill, leaſt otherwiſe wee take the wing, and follow after vanitie, with the firſt winde that bloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:156:29"/>
God then being called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by vs, when wee are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der croſſes and afflictions, which hee layes vpon vs, he ſtrengthens vs with his grace, according as he ſees it needfull for our ſalvation. Loe the very end of theſe croſſes, even of the croſſes, which in the doubtfull wayes of this world, better then any other guide, or marke, doe correct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs.<note place="margin">The burden of bearing the Croſſe of Chriſt.</note> But vnder the croſſe principally of his Chriſt, vnder the true croſſe when it is layd vpon our ſhoulders, then we feele the helpe of his ſtrength; when we are called to ſuffer for his Name, for his Truth and for his Word; and indeede divers are the natures of thes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:156:29"/>croſſes, every maner of way. By theſe he hath ordained to humble vs, to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto the true faith, wherein conſequently, God interpoſeth himſelfe, yea he even participates with vs, he ſuffers, and ſuffers with vs himſelfe. And therefore in this croſſe, the faithfull ſeek for comfort from God by their prayer; in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, their prayer begins with giving of thankes, he praiſeth God for doing him the honour to ſuffer for his Name; to chooſe him as it were for a Champion of his quarrell, he reioyceth, he glories, he boaſteth in his ſufferings, and in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of our Saviour even
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:156:30"/>reioyced after they were ſcourged by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.41. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo farre boaſted, as to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in his tribulations; Becauſe theſe afflictions were not ſo much his, as Chriſts. <hi>Becauſe he fulfilled the reſt of the afflictions of Chriſt in his fleſh, for his body ſake, that is, the Church.</hi> Col. 1.24. Becauſe the Chriſtian is aſſured in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for Chriſt, that Chriſt ſuffers with him, takes part of his ſorrowes, burthens himſelfe, and diſburthens him. And from hence did the glorious Martyrs, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in their Martyrdom. When thou ſeeſt them then halfe burned, their bowells iſſuing forth, and yet lifted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:156:30"/>vp their eyes to Chriſt by prayer, nay rather by ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, brake through the noyſe of the flames. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O fleſh and bloud tell me here; if Chriſt were not there, if he aſſiſted them not effectually, or clothed them not really with his power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the violence of that Element, and againſt the crueltie of thoſe who ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens it againſt them; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou that there could be any one found, that could ſtand? And from whence then came ſo many millions? Yea where could there haue beene found any one, that ſhould reſolue with himſelfe, to die for one dead, to ſuffer himſelfe to be tortured, for one Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:156:31"/>and from whence then could this come, if it were not in that Chriſt liveth in them; and in them, &amp; with them, is crucified? Verily in them who caſt their burden vpon the Lord; the Sonne coeternall with the Father, not to ſhake off their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but the more couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to beare it, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by his preſence, ſtrengthened by his hand. And therefore in other croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the wonder conſiſteth herein, that the Lord being called vpon in faith, doth graciouſly deliver thee; But loe here the myracle is, in that the faithfull, againſt ſence, reaſon, and nature, offer themſelues vp in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto God; their fleſh
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:156:31"/>and bloud, their humaine reaſon, altogether fleſh and bloud, renouncing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to confeſſe Chriſt. And ſeeing it is impoſſible of themſelues, whence is it then, for the honor of God, but by God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The burden of our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note>And ſo much for the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Croſſe and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, when it overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs. Now followes that croſſe, which concernes our calling, and function, vnto which God calleth vs. A true burthen alſo, for there is none ſo ſmall in regard of the weakneſſe of our nature, vnder the which our ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders doe not bow, yet be it never ſo great, in his power, who calls vs thereunto; wee need not feare to paſſe; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:156:32"/>alwayes, it be a true calling, by which he makes it his owne. And therefore the Apoſtle exhorts every one, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1. to walke worthy his calling, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that grace which is given vs, according to the meaſure of the gift of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> To walke, is not ſimplie to goe, but to hold a certaine way, and to ayme at the true end thereof; and beſides, <hi>in a mans Calling,</hi> to looke he haue it from God; who is a God of order, who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines, and who imployes all his Creatures; every one to ſome certaine thing; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtone to haue a certaine place in his building. He that walkes in his Calling, ſets all his paths vnto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:156:32"/>walkes alwayes well, though he halt in it; he that ſtrayeth from thence, what ſpeed ſoever he makes, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the further out of his way, and for the moſt part goes backward. Well then, every calling hath his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or rather his croſſe, yet not without ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts, and helpe from aboue, even from him who hath created all things. He I ſay, with the ſame power, bountie, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preſerveth them, and directs all things. For let vs not thinke, that he hath leſſe care, or takes more pleaſure to comfort an Artificer in his ſhopp, then he doth a Prince in his Throne: a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, as well as a Common
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:156:33"/>wealth; for every where where his name is called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he hearkens, he heares, he puts to his helping hand without exception, without acception of perſons; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him who hath equally made them, the braſſe is as deare as the gold, the hempe as the flax, the courſe cloth as the ſcarlet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But in the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of thoſe, whom hee calleth to the conducting of his people, of his Church, this bountifull providence doth more appeare; becauſe ſhee is ſet as it were vpon a hill, becauſe they are, or ought to be, the light of the world, as alſo becauſe the Lord in his holy Scriptures hath left them for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:156:33"/>
Art thou then in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Calling,<note place="margin">1. In the Magiſtracy.</note> be it either polliticke, or eccleſiaſticke; and doſt thou meete with a ſtiffenecked people, being ready every houre to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure; with gyants, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their heads againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, againſt whom thou art every houre to pronounce, and lay open Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? A hard Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, troubleſome, rough, &amp; hard to vndergoe, if thou onely looke into thy ſelfe, but looke vnto God, who hath impoſed this Calling vpon thee; doe not thou therefore ſhake off thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as another <hi>Ionas. Who fled vnto Tarſis, from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord,</hi> and ſhipt himſelfe at <hi>Ioppa,</hi> who meets
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:156:34"/>with him amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the waues; <hi>Whether ſhall I goe from thy ſpirit,</hi> ſayth the Prophet. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.7. or <hi>whether ſhall I flie from thy preſence.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather humble thy ſelfe before his face, acknowledg thy imbecillitie, ſeeke thy ſtrength from him, take thy warrant from his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. What, oh Lord, is duſt and aſhes, that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt expect ſuch ſtrength, ſuch ſervice, if thou put not to thy helping hand, if thou worke not in it? There needs no greater matter then lyce to confound the wiſe; the ruine of the pride of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Well then, Lord, worke thou; <hi>Who am I Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18 19.22.23.24.) <hi>and what is my houſe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:156:34"/>that thou haſt brought me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto? is this the manner of men,</hi> is there any thing here whereof man can preſume, or promiſe ought vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? But he takes him at his word, wherein his glory is interreſſed. And ſayth, <hi>for thy promiſe ſake, and according to thy heart, thou haſt done all this greatneſſe, &amp;c. to get thee a name, and a people for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> And where his calling meets, there his promiſe ſecretly comes betweene. <hi>Who am I</hi> alſo ſaith his Son <hi>Salomon.</hi> 1 Kings 3. <hi>to iudge this ſo great a people, &amp;c.</hi> Alas, <hi>I am but a childe, who knowes not how to goe in and out before them.</hi> And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Lord, from whom every good gift comes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:156:35"/>giues him, to him I ſay (who acknowledging his owne incapacitie; ſeekes the ſupply thereof in his grace) <hi>a wiſe and an vnderſtanding heart,</hi> a habit very neceſſary for a King; he giues him more then he requireth, <hi>riches and honour,</hi> things ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeemely. Alſo, <hi>who am I,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3.11. that I ſhould goe vnto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and that I ſhould bring the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Exod. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Alas Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>neither yeſterday nor before ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, am I a man of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſpeech,</hi> but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>of a ſlow mouth and tongre.</hi> Now the buſineſſe was to ſpeake vnto a great Prince, to perſwade him of ſtrange offenſiue things;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:156:35"/>
               <hi>but I,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>will be with thee;</hi> and beholde the ſignes: <hi>Who made the mouth of man, who made the dumbe, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 4.12. <hi>I will be with thy mouth, and will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by thy hand I will doe that which thou ſhalt haue to ſay; that we might know the great priviledge thoſe haue, whom God ſets on worke in reſpect of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thoſe whom the Princes of the earth imploy in their ſervices, if they be not adorned with exquiſite qualities, ſhall but ſhame both themſelues and their Maiſters: but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thoſe who are aſſured of their calling; nay of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, who workes all in all,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:156:36"/>and in all things, it cannot be but they ſhould be able to diſcharge it. But yet in humility feeling their owne imbecillity, and for the moſt part, aboue that they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined they could haue done. Becauſe they worke by him, and he in them, by whoſe power the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of things worke the contrary effect to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as namely, heate to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, fury to cherriſh, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to cauſe it ſelfe to be feared, the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mering tong, to be able to perſwade, a childe to pronounce judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea bondage it ſelfe, to rule.</p>
            <p>Now this is alſo in reſpect of this confidence, which they beleeue they haue a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:156:36"/>right vnto, and ſo they haue indeed, to caſt themſelues vpon the Lord, when evill oppreſſeth them. <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> being affrighted with the <hi>Moabites;</hi> he proclaimes a faſt, craues helpe from God. But how? <hi>they come,</hi> ſaith he, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. <hi>to diſpoſſeſſe vs of thine inheritance, which thou gaveſt vs to poſſeſſe. O our God, wilt not thou iudge them,</hi> and the rather becauſe the caſe goeth thus ill with vs, there being <hi>us ſtrength in vs, to ſtand before ſo great a multitude:</hi> But ſayth he, <hi>our eyes are towards thee;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven towards the Lord, who forthwith puts his hand to the burthen, and anſweres him by his Prophet; <hi>feare not, you ſhall not neede to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:156:37"/>fight, but God;</hi> beholde he commeth to their reſeue, and he alone will doe all for you; <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord;</hi> take you no other care but to prayſe mee. So impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and behoouefull it is vnto every ſervant of God in ſuch occaſions, to engage the Lord in his cauſe, and to haue no intereſt therein but his juſtice, his ſanctuary, his glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> comes vnto King <hi>Ezekias.</hi> 2 Kings 18. and 19. Let not thy God, ſaith he, in whom thou tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt deceiue thee; thou ſeeſt what the King of the <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> hath done vnto all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries; haue their Gods delivered them, that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:156:37"/>thou ſhouldeſt hope better of thine? But what doth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias</hi> in this anguiſh, Lord, ſayth he, thou art the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or alone God of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, belongs it not then properly vnto thee; and this argument which he makes; comparing the Idolls of the Nations with thee, ſhall he be left vnpuniſhed of thee; of thee, I ſay, the Creator of heaven and earth? Encline thine eare then Lord, and hearken vnto the words of this Champion, whom <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> hath ſent to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the living God; Deliver vs therfore, O Lord, out of his hand, that all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may know, that thou Lord art the onely God. Then comes the Prophet
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:156:38"/>
               <hi>Eſay</hi> vnto him, and allures him in the name of the Lord, that his prayer was heard, and that the Lord tooke knowledge thereof, making the cauſe his owne; who in the ſame night ſmot <hi>Senacherib</hi> and his Armie, by the hand of his Angell. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes to this purpoſe in more expreſſe termes; and for the ground of this Confidence, this holy boldneſſe to caſt his burden vpon the Lord, he takes his meaſure from faith, faith grounded on knowledge. For is it not ſayd, that <hi>God ſpake vnto him face to face?</hi> The people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> being nouriſhed and fed by myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſo many yeares in the deſert, being enemy to their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:156:38"/>owne good, would not goe into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but murmured thereupon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and rebelled ſo farre againſt <hi>Moſes. Numb.</hi> 14. that they were ready to ſtone him. The Lord being wrath at this their infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he tells <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he is weary of them, and that he will deſtroy them. O but Lord, ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> what then will the Nations ſay; for the <hi>Cananites</hi> cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that thou Lord <hi>art ſeene of this people face to face; that thy Cloud,</hi> thy protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ſtandeth over them,</hi> and that thou haſt expreſſely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken the ſafe conduct of this people; and now they will ſay, that thou haſt kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, becauſe thou waſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:156:39"/>not able to bring them into the Land, which thou hadſt ſworne vnto their Fathers to giue them: vrging God vpon the point of his owne honour, jealous in regard of man; no leſſe jealous in reſpect of God, who giveth himſelfe the title of <hi>iealous;</hi> thereby inducing him (as a meanes) to reſtraine his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and pardon his people. <hi>As I liue,</hi> ſayth the Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>the whole earth ſhall be filled with my glory; with my glory</hi> in a double reſpect; firſt, becauſe theſe murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall not ſee the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Land; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thoſe who continued faithfull, ſhall poſſeſſe the Land for inheritance; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by being equally magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:156:39"/>both in my mercy, and in my juſtice. Let all this be granted, may ſome one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but this was in the time of myracles. True; but my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles were heretofore done from time to time, to none other end, but to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to thee, as a glimpſe of that infinite power, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> worketh, and diſpoſeth, all theſe myracles of the whole world, which being perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, are to thee no longer myracles. The Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lords hand is not ſhortened, that it cannot helpe, nor his eare heavy that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare.</hi> Whereas the globe of the earth, ſince ſo many ages paſt, continueth hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ayre, holding by nothing, but by the onely
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:156:40"/>powerfull will of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; is it not myraculous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at this day? It may be, more myraculous then the firſt day that he framed it; whereas the Church alſo continueth, being but a point as it were in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of this Chaos of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, yet ſwimmes aloft, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſhewing the head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue water, amiddeſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waues, is alſo no leſſe a myracle, yea and it may be alſo more, in the middeſt of ſo many diſordered Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and of ſo many flouds; then when ſhee floated in the Arke, or paſſed through the red Sea. The workes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the Lord, though leſſe viſible to our eyes, are not therefore leſſe reall in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:156:40"/>themſelues, nor leſſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the minds of the faithfull. The Prophet ſaith <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. that <hi>our iniquities haue made a ſeperation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and him, cauſeth him to hide his face from vs.</hi> But let vs onely turne our eyes towards him, and he will returne againe wholly towards vs. In like propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards an eſtate, nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Cittie, family, or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſon, which ſhall call vpon him; where his Church, where his ſervice, where his feare, hath taken vp their dwelling. My ſoule which art often perplexed in thy ſelfe, in anguiſh for his Church, amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waues which toſſeth her, and thee in her, tempted to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:156:41"/>caſt off thy burthen, haſt thou caſt it vpon the Lord, and hath he eaſed thee? How oft diſpayring of all humaine helpes, haſt thou ſayd vnto him; <hi>how long;</hi> and did the Lord ever fayle to anſwer thee; yea to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee by viſible effects, more intelligible then his wordes?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. In the Miniſtry.</note>The like may be ſayd of them who are called of God vnto an eccleſiaſticall func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; As heretofore of the Prophets denouncing the judgements of God againſt Kings, and againſt Nations; after them the Apoſtles ſent to Preach the onely word of ſalvation vnto the ends of the world, to the ruine of falſe gods, and of their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:156:41"/>the pretended protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of States and of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales. Thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles being conſequently bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their cauſe againſt the perſecution of thoſe who diſgraced them. And ſo in like manner thoſe, who in the Church, as they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſers of the Goſpell, hold their place at this day. For with what confidence, and with what wiſedome, did <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Elizeus</hi> with their cloakes ſtand againſt Kings, Princes, and the Prieſts of <hi>Iſrael; Iohn Baptiſt</hi> with his garment of Cammels haire, withſtood King <hi>Herod.</hi> The Apoſtles being poorefiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and vnlearned, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the ruine of Sathans
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:156:42"/>kingdome, the Conqueſt of the world, vnder the Croſſe of Chriſt? Therefore let thoſe who ſucceede them in this office, accept of this Commiſſion in all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſay, Lord, who am I, that thou haſt called mee therevnto; And what man is he, though never ſo great, that is ſufficient for it? But yet as vncapable as I am, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the leaſt in my ſelfe; yet being aſſiſted by thee, who art the greateſt, what am I not able to doe? For ſo <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> ſayth;<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Woe is me for I am vndone, becauſe I am a man of polluted lips;</hi> no ſooner had God touched his lips with a liue coale from the Altar, but he changeth his ſpeech; <hi>Who ſhall I ſend,</hi> ſayth the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:156:42"/>Lord, he anſweres cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, <hi>behold I am here, ſend mee.</hi> But with what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? Say vnto this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in hearing you ſhall heare, <hi>and not vnderſtand</hi> &amp;c. Make fatte the heart of this people, &amp;c. Let a man haue ten times as many naturall gifts, as <hi>Eſay</hi> had; could he without this aſſiſtance from the Lord, haue vndergone this Charge? In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Prophet <hi>Ieremy; I haue ſet thee this day,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>over Nations, and over Kingdomes, that thou ſhouldeſt plucke vp, and pull downe, that thou ſhouldest build and plant.</hi> A pooreſilly Prieſt of <hi>Anothoth.</hi> Iere. 1.1. Therefore he that will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, let him yet wonder at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:156:43"/>it? <hi>Ah Lord God, beholde I cannot ſpeake,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for I am but a childe.</hi> And behold! he had no ſooner touched his mouth, but preſently he girdeth vp his reynes, and is reſolved, that whereas be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>before he acknowledged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be but a childe, now he begins to be a man; and the terror of men. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Chriſt tells the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Yee ſhall be brought before Kings; and you ſhall beare witneſſe of mee even to the ends of the earth;</hi> being but men of meane condition, to ſtand aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the onely looke of a man of authoritie, the bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt amongſt them, at the word of a poore ſilly mayd. But take no care, ſayth the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:156:43"/>Lord, I will put that into your mouth at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, which you ſhall ſay. <hi>Feare not,</hi> ſaith he alſo vnto S. <hi>Paul, hold not thy peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>for I am with thee.</hi> And what he ſayd to them, let vs take as ſpoken vnto all; vnto all who are Miniſters of the ſame word, being never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of his ſpirit, nor of his ſtrength, <hi>to the pulling downe,</hi> ſ yth the Apoſtle, <hi>of ſtrong holds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>caſting downe all counſells, and every high thing which exalts it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing every thought into capti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vity, to the obedience of Chriſt having vengeance ready pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt all d ſobedience.</hi> What can be ſaid more? And be not diſmayd at this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:156:44"/>that the liue coale hath not touched thy lippes, nor the breath of Chriſt, breathed vpon thee; the ſignes of his word and ſpirit; provided that thou haſt his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with thee, and his word in thy mouth. Thoſe ſignes had their place once for all; <hi>Timothy</hi> had not received them, whom notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Apoſtle ſummons before God, and before the Lord Ieſus, vnto whom he ſhall giue an account. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. &amp; 2. Where he ſayth, <hi>Preach the word;</hi> But how, <hi>in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, rebuke, exhort, doe the worke of an Evangeliſt.</hi> It may be, thou ſhalt be hated of thoſe which are without, and deſpiſed ſometimes of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:156:44"/>thoſe within; wilt thou haue it bteter cheape then the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of the Vineyard? Which of the Prophets, or which of the Apoſtles, were not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſtoned, and vexed? Say with <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. the 31. <hi>I haue beene a reproach vnto my adverſaries, vnto my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours much more, and thoſe of my acquaintance ſeeing mee, fled from me.</hi> But Lord, <hi>I haue ſayd, thou art my God, I truſt in thee.</hi> Learne thou alſo with the ſame great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7.8. <hi>to goe through honour and diſhonor, through good report and evill report, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armor of righteouſneſſe, on the right hand and on the left.</hi> Be not diſcouraged alſo, if thou
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:156:45"/>falleſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a barren ground, as it were ſowed with ſalt; vpon a brutiſh and ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked people. <hi>Who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved,</hi> ſayth <hi>Eſay, our report?</hi> And after him, our Saviour himſelfe. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.36. And of ſixe hundred thouſand which went ont of <hi>Aegypt</hi> with <hi>Moſes</hi> ready armed, how few of them entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of promiſe? Of ſo many people whom our Lord had healed, had preached vnto, even the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall word; how few of them did beleeue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued following him? How many thinkeſt thou were there of them, who helpt to blaſpheme him at his death? And notwithſtanding, did God therefore ceaſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:156:45"/>
               <hi>Canaan</hi> by lyne vnto his people? The word of the Croſſe, did that ceaſe to ſubdue the world, yea to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the world, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the world? Heare our Saviour Chriſt himſelfe in <hi>Eſay</hi> the 49.4. complaining, and in his conſolation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thou thine; <hi>I ſayd I haue laboured in vaine, and ſpent my ſtrength for nothing, notwithſtanding my reward is with the Lord, and my worke with my God.</hi> The Lord who anſweres him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>I haue heard thee</hi> (hold it as if it were already done) <hi>in an acceptable time, in the day of ſalvation haue I ſuccoured thee.</hi> It muſt be a long time after, leaſt thou ſhouldſt waxe weary, yet in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:156:46"/>his time, in an acceptable time, in a time by him eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally pre-ordained. And thus of this word which thou publiſheſt, to the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his truth, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing of errors, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the kingdom of his Chriſt, to the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the tyranny of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, waite for the fruit, and expect the effect in his time; but in the meane time, be not thou careleſſe, but vſe all the means to manure the ground, which he hath committed vnto thee. And ſay vnto him, Lord, this ground will be but Iron, if the heaven be of Braſſe. From thy onely bleſſing, I waite for the fruit of my labour; by thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:156:46"/>I plant, and in this hope I water. And thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, how in the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Callings, we are to comfort our ſelues in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Is there no other burden which we are to caſt vpon the Lord? Yes verily, the weightieſt doth yet remaine, the burden of ſinne. Sinne,<note place="margin">The burden of ſinne.</note> as light as it ſeemes vnto vs, which by no meanes can ſtand in the ballance of ſo juſt a God, muſt needs be very heavie, &amp; moſt waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe it provokes his anger, &amp; preſſeth vs downe to hell, by an offence againſt an infinite Maieſtie, againſt an infinite anger. Sinne which lyeth vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, being the liuelieſt,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:156:47"/>the moſt ſenſible, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt part of the ſoule, doth vexe and diſquiet it. Whereas the griefe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, lyeth properly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſenſes: perplexities in our Callings, lyes vpon our ſpirits. But ſinne was the cauſe, that made our firſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after the commiſſion thereof, to hide himſelfe from the Lord; and to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the very ſhaking of the leaues. As alſo that <hi>Caine</hi> having perceived his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, was ſmitten with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected &amp; pale countenance; and the ſentence being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, was as a burthen and puniſhment vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; <hi>My iniquitie,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>is greater then I am able to beare,</hi> Gen. 4. though he had
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:156:47"/>all the world at command, yet he findes himſelfe in a ſtraight in his ſoule. Even ſo the beſt men, though more tender in Conſcience, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and patient in all ſorts of afflictions, yet are here impatient, &amp; ſtooping vnder this burthen, lie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed in, and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>David</hi> who ſo often repeateth in the <hi>Pſalme</hi> 56. I truſt in God, and will not feare what the arme of fleſh can doe vnto me, yet findes himſelfe preſſed downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of his olde man: <hi>My finne, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> ſaith he, <hi>is continually before mee;</hi> I ſee nothing elſe, <hi>I haue ſinned againſt thee; O turne thy face from mine iniquities.</hi> Not content with this, as
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:156:48"/>elſe-where to ſay vnto God, <hi>haue pittie on me;</hi> but here, he calls to his ſuccour, <hi>the greatneſſe of his compaſſions,</hi> the full depth of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; to purge, waſh, and waſh againe, to blot out his ſinnes; to create in him a cleane heart, to renue in him a right ſpirit, feeling no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in himſelfe, which might abide the light of his countenance, which turned not vnto him in ſteade of a pleaſing light, a countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce iuſtly inflamed with wrath. And thus that great Apoſtle alſo, who was joyous and triumphing over all ſorts of afflictions, ſhrunke at this; thoſe others being pledges of helpe from God, but this a kindler of his wrath; thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:156:48"/>calling vnto him as it were from heaven, and cauſing him to haſten his pace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, as at the cry of his Children: But this which turneth away his eye, and ſequeſters his preſence from vs, makes him forget, yea and to renounce his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>I repont that I haue made man;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> 
               <hi>my ſpirit ſhall not alwayes ſtriue with him;</hi> it makes him to conſent, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſolue to blot out his Image with a curſe, and to determine in himſelfe, to deſtroy even all fleſh from the earth with a Deluge. And therefore let vs not thinke it ſtrange, that he changeth here both tune and voice; that he who ſaid <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.12.13. <hi>I know and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:156:49"/>am inſtructed, how to be full, and how to be hungry, as well to abound, as to want; I am able to doe all things in Christ who ſtrengthens me.</hi> But now with a languiſhing ſpeech, changing his tune; ſayth, <hi>Sinne dwelleth in me; and in mee there dwelleth no good thing; I haue not the power to performe that which is good; I finde this Law in me, that when I would doe good, evill is preſent with mee.</hi> How far off was he here from doing all things? But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary addeth;<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
               <hi>There is a law in my members which leades me captiue to the Law of ſinne,</hi> delivers me bound hand &amp; foote, my feete fettered with ſinne; and conſequently to death, &amp; hell, the rewards of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:156:49"/>ſinne. What burthen thinke we then he felt, who before was ſo valiant vnder all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burdens, when he cryes out in the end,<note place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note> 
               <hi>wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> Well then, ſeeing ſinne in it ſelfe is ſo heavie, in regard of God who is puritie and juſtice it ſelfe; yea to hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſo odious; who ſhall be ſo bold then as to caſt this burden vpon the Lord? Shall we ſay vnto him as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> did after his fall. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.12. <hi>The woman whom thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me, gaue me of the tree to eate?</hi> Or as the prophane ones mentioned by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 19. Why haſt thou not made vs better? <hi>Whereof complaineſt thou? for
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:156:50"/>who can reſiſt thy will?</hi> Thus covering their ſinne with blaſphemie; a ſort of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who Conteſt againſt the Creator, whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſleepeth not. What then, is there no remedy to eaſe this burden? Is it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the leſſon w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> here the Prophet giveth vs? And if wee muſt lye downe vnder this burthen, what will it profit vs to be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved vnder any other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den? yea rather here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally hath it place, here it is wherein God meaneth properly to ſhew that <hi>his mercy is aboue all his workes;</hi> to powre out his mercy, and to open his bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that by executing juſtice, he may make his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:156:50"/>chiefe worke to appeare. <hi>To vs</hi> (ſayth the Prophet) <hi>a childe is borne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>to vs a ſonne is given, and his government is layd vpon his ſhoulder; His government,</hi> that is, his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to ſaue his people from their ſinnes; <hi>vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> for as much as he hath layd the Croſſe vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and vnto the Croſſe hath nayled our ſinnes. And therefore the ſame Prophet ſayth, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.5.6.7. <hi>He hath borne our griefes, and taken on him our ſorrowes, he was bruiſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Lord hath made to come vpon him the iniquities of vs all, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him.</hi> Vpon him, even vpon his ſhoulder; therefore is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:156:51"/>added, that his name <hi>ſhall be cased Wonderfull, Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, the mightie and ſtrong God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of peace.</hi> No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but he, could be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch a burthen, our <hi>Emanuell, God with vs. The Lambe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> ſayth S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, that taketh away the ſinne of the world;</hi> hath borne them, ſayth S. <hi>Peter.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>in his bodie vpon the tree; being made ſinne,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. <hi>that we might be made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in him; and made a curſe for vs,</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>that the bleſſing of Abraham might come vpon vs by him.</hi> But thinke not here that thou who delighteſt thy ſelfe in thy ſinnes, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:156:51"/>flattereſt thy ſelfe therein, who makeſt triumphs, who art iolly and merry vnder this burden, that thou haſt any part in theſe benefits, or that Chriſt ſhould bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den himſelfe with thy ſins, wherewith thou feeleſt not thy ſelfe burdened, thou muſt firſt feele them. <hi>Vnto whom ſhall I haue reſpect,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>Eſay</hi> 66.2. <hi>vnto him that is afflicted, and hath a bruiſed ſpirit, and trembleth at my word;</hi> to ſuch a one is it ſayd,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.20</note> that <hi>where ſinne aboundeth, grace doth more abound.</hi> On the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary he ſayth, away from mee, yee workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who make a trade there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who make you pillowes thereof to ſleepe vpon.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:156:52"/>
               <hi>Should we ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 6.1.15</note> ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>that grace might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound? God forbid. Know ye not that vnto whom ſoever yee yeeld your ſelues ſervants to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, his ſervants yee are vnto whom yee obey, be it of ſinne vnto death, or of obedience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to righteouſneſſe.</hi> Yee then, that are ſervants of ſinne, who ſuffer it to raigne qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly in you, what can you expect but death, even eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death.</p>
            <p>But wouldeſt thou haue part in this promiſe, to be eaſed of this burthen of ſin? Then confeſſe thy ſinne freely vnto the Lord with ſighes and teares. <hi>So long as I held my peace,</hi> ſayth <hi>David, my bones waxed olde, thy hand was heavie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:156:52"/>was changed into the drought of Sommer.</hi> Pſal. 32.3.4.5. See him here as it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed vnder his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; <hi>I acknowledge my ſinne vnto thee: I ſayd, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my tranſgreſſions vnto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the puniſhment of my ſinne.</hi> See how he is eaſed both of his ſinne and puniſhment. Say vnto him then with the Prophet <hi>Daniell; I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> 
               <hi>I haue done wickedly; vnto thee belongeth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but vnto mee confuſion of face; but Lord doe thou forgiue:</hi> And doubt not but Chriſt will ſay vnto thy ſoule, if thy ſoule ſpeake truely; <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee, goe in peace;</hi> thy peace is made with GOD,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:156:53"/>be at peace in thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for he alſo it is, in whom this promiſe is <hi>yea, and Amen;</hi> In him who calleth vs, <hi>Math.</hi> the 11.28. ſaying; <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that travayle, and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie laden,</hi> if with <hi>afflictions, I will refreſh you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.18.</note> For <hi>as I haue ſuffered and was temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo am I of power to ſuccour thoſe who are tempted.</hi> If with <hi>perplexities;</hi> alas! are not your Callings properly my yoke? <hi>My yoke is eaſie, and my burden is light,</hi> ſeeing I haue layd it vpon you; yea, if of <hi>ſinne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>am I not come to deſtroy the workes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> to vnlooſe ſinne, and to ſaue ſinners? <hi>Come then, and you ſhall finde reſt vnto you ſoules.</hi> To him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:156:53"/>with the Father and the holy Spirit, for the riches of his grace, be given from our ſoules, all honour and glory for ever and ever, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:54"/>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:156:54"/>
            <head>AN HOMILIE VPON THESE WORDS;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>My peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue vnto you; not as the world giueth it,</p>
                  <bibl>&amp;c. <hi>Ioh. 14.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR LORD IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Paſſion, making as it were his laſt will and teſtament among his Apoſtles, he leaues and giues vnto them his peace,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:156:55"/>it behooveth vs to knowe wherein this Legacie and gift conſiſteth; ſeeing it ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tends it ſelfe vnto all who haue need thereof,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> 
               <hi>who by their Word haue beleeved in his Name;</hi> and ſo much the more, becauſe that in the words of our Saviour there is alwayes a myſtery, a heavenly treaſure hidden vnder the earthly ſound of his words, which we muſt ſearch and looke into by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining of them, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the ſence according to the worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of his perſon who vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them. For example, When he ſpeaketh of waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs, of nouriſhing vs, and of healing vs, wee muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand himſelfe to be our
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:156:55"/>waſhing, our nouriſhment, our healing, wee beeing taught thereby to raiſe the ſignification of theſe words vnto the pitch of his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning who ſpeaketh; and thereby to apprehend both the effects of his holy ſpirit in vs, but chiefely in our ſoules, being naturally ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall. If thou didſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thy ſelfe with a leſſe gift, <hi>Alexander</hi> would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thee, that if it ſuffice thy baſe minde, yet it is not worthy of his magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And our Saviour Chriſt would anſwere thee, who wouldeſt content thy ſelfe with temporall bleſſings, that he came not into the world, nor ſuffered ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny things to pamper thy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:156:56"/>belly, or thee, to giue to thy bodie all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentments. And therfore the queſtion is here of a bleſſing and comfort truly ſpirituall. For his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit whom he ordaineth the true Executor of this his Teſtament, will ſufficiently witneſſe vnto vs the nature of this Legacie; <hi>The Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>who is the holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will ſend in my name.</hi> A ſpirituall Executor, as well both of a ſpirituall diſpoſition, as of a ſpirituall donation; of the donation which hee hath granted vnto vs, even of all that which he hath gotten, and purchaſed for vs by his life, and the price of his life; I ſay, of his life, from the very firſt entrance wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:156:56"/>even the heavenly Hoſts haue ſung;<note place="margin">Luk. 2.14</note> 
               <hi>Glory be to God on high, and peace on earth, good will towards men.</hi> Even his Paſſion, whereof in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preceding ages, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did foretell vnto vs, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>The chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him.</hi> Both procuring peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene heaven and earth; the onely reconciliation of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I leaue vnto you,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>my peace.</hi> But what peace? Truely vnder this word <hi>peace,</hi> many bleſſings are comprehended, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe many evills excluded. And the ſtricteſt way wee take it, it ſtretcheth it ſelfe very farre, namely, vnto the good of civill ſocietie; The
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:156:57"/>which cannot be better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended then by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For example, domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call quarrels being the ruine of families; publicke warre, the combuſtion of States; an abridgement of all cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that either the malice of men, or the miſchiefe of ages can bring forth. Here then he leaveth vnto vs a peace, which preſerveth vs therein, ſuch a peace as a Father may leaue vnto his Children by his Will and Teſtament, ſetting bounds touching their portions, curbing in their ſtrifes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions. Or like to thoſe of a good Prince, who in good pollicie, paſſeth them over to his Subiects after
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:156:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>his death; vnder which peace, every one ſitteth quietly vnder his owne vine and figge tree. Well then, ſhall this peace be worthy to be vttered by the mouth of our Saviour, of him who is King of Kings, the Father of Spirits; of the Prince of peace, even of peace it ſelfe, of our Saviour, God and man; God borne amongſt vs, God who dyed for vs? Let vs looke for no greater nor more excellent thing. Let it be graunted that hee leaue vnto vs the peace which <hi>Auguſtus</hi> himſelfe had; what will it profit thee if the fire conſume thy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt? If the worme gnaw thy conſcience? If thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience torment thee? Let
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:156:58"/>vs graunt, that thy fieldes bring forth plentifully, that thy trade proſpers, that thy familie flouriſheth, that thy perſon triumpheth, What will all that benefit thee, if thy taſte be gone, thy ſpirit feaveriſh, thy ſoule vpon the racke, eternall death in thy boſome, a hell in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, even then when thou thinkeſt moſt of all to haue made a covenant with death, an agreement with hell, to haue confirmed thy peace with every Creature; &amp; yet art thou odious even vnto thy Creator? Oft times there is an externall peace, which cauſeth civill warres; a bodily well fare, which kindles in vs ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes, temporal good things
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:156:58"/>which preiudice the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? Nay, let vs yet goe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; even he who tells vs plainely, that he came not to ſet peace in the world, but warre; who forewarneth his Apoſtles, that for his ſake, houſholds ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, Kingdomes trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, his Diſciples perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from place to place; That even then, they ſhould eſteeme themſelues happie, when they ſhall be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his name. He hath not promiſed vs a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and fraudulent peace, which flatters many times the bodie, to the hurt of the ſoule, and makes vs forſake our inheritance, for a peaſe, and for very huskes; and therefore he addes further;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:156:59"/>I giue vnto you <hi>my peace, not the worlds peace,</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe make your account to haue the world for your enemy. What elſe doe wee ſee in all the liues of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, for the ſpace of ſo many ages? in the death of ſo many Martyrs? Not the peace of this world; how long ſhall we be children, and how long vnder the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip of the Law, onely to taſte and deſire milke and hony? Not peace with men; ſeeing for this cauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved that God ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come man, and that heaven ſhould come downe vpon earth? Could not ſome <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> haue given vs that peace? But <hi>my peace,</hi> peace with God, peace in our
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:156:59"/>ſelues, with our ſelues, which the onely <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> the <hi>father of eternitie,</hi> can giue vnto vs. Even he as the Prophet tells vs, <hi>Mich.</hi> 5.3.5. <hi>whoſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth haue beene from everlaſting,</hi> of whom it is written, <hi>this man ſhall be the peace;</hi> being able both to accompliſh it, and to giue it, and is that very peace himſelfe. The governor of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> of whoſe comming, <hi>Haggai</hi> the Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Hag. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſet peace in this place,</hi> to wit, in my Temple, in my Church, <hi>ſayth the Lord of Hoſtes.</hi> A peace, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding far different from that which carnall people, which fleſh and bloud com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends; Seeing that the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:156:60"/>government of this Prince of peace, is vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. A proofe, that he ſhould haue much to ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; even this governour, whole kingdome is wholly diſdained, throwne downe, and cruſhed, and yet therein properly coſiſteth the peace which he bringeth vs, that in his wounding, we might and healing; for what tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall peace can wee expect from him, and by him, whoſe life in this world was a continuall warrefare? He will ſay vnto vs, Shall the ſervant thinke to be better intreated, then the Sonne, then the heire, then the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Familie?</p>
            <p>Well then, ſayth he, <hi>I giue you my peace;</hi> mine; ſuch a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:156:60"/>peace, as no other but I could make;<note place="margin">I.</note> peace with God, whom no other but Man God could vndertake. <hi>Your iniquities had made a ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paration betweene you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 59.2.</note> 
               <hi>and your God,</hi> and hath made him to hide his face from you, nor would he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to looke vpon you, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could he, but in his an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, and to your ruine, and eternall damnation. And therefore behold now, how that by my mediation you haue peace with him; and that in my bloud which I am ready to ſhed for you, is made the propitiation for your ſinnes; a myſtery here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hidden from other ages, but now a myracle; which will fill all the world
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:156:61"/>with aſtoniſhment, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all humane wiſdome in their diſcourſes; whence it is that the Prophet long agoe being raviſhed in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, cryeth out and ſayth, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 52.7. <hi>Oh how beautifull are the feete of him vpon the mountaines, who bringeth glad tydings, who proclaime peace and ſalvation vnto Iſraell.</hi> And you haue this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be of them, not onely to partake of this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but alſo to be the heraulds &amp; diſpenſers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to proclaime the benefit of my death, &amp; the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins vnto the world, to manifeſt vnto <hi>Sion</hi> this good tydings. Thy God reigneth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.7. and yet not with an iron rod; for
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:156:61"/>who then could beare it? But with meekeneſſe and with mercie, <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. Whereof you inioy the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of his kingdome, that is, <hi>righteouſneſſe, peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 14.17. And therefore wee reade ſo often in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtles; <hi>Grace be with you and peace from Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Peace through grace, for without the grace of God, there is no peace. And therefore ſo often it is ſayd, Mercy and peace are mett together, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. one proceeding from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Iude</hi> the 2. verſe, and both of them in Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Thence it is, that the Lord himſelfe tells vs. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 48.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 57.21. that there
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:156:62"/>is no peace for the wicked, becauſe there can bee no peace where there is no grace; What ſoever peace they ſeeme to haue in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, yet alwaies (ſayth the Prophet) they are like <hi>a troubled Sea.</hi> And there can be no grace but onely in Chriſt. In Chriſt, in whoſe name God <hi>ſends to proclaime peace</hi> every where.<note place="margin">Act. 10.36.</note> In Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.14. Rom. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>who himſelfe is our peace; In whom being iuſtified by faith, wee haue peace with God,</hi> peace with all men. Truly that peace, which we ſeeke, and which wee finde in him. But here it is time now to examine what is the efficacie thereof.</p>
            <p>Certainely it is ſuch, that in this peace alone we finde
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:156:62"/>whatſoever is in all others; and yet in all others put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, we finde nothing of that which is found in this peace perfect in it ſelfe, and makes a ſupply to all others. Now three kindes of peace are vſually reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And firſt, peace with all men; as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. <hi>if it be poſſible as much as lyeth in you, haue peace with all men.</hi> But hath a man it, when he will; or did even the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe obtaine it? And ſeeing ſuch manner of ſpeeches are doubtfull, is it not rather to be deſired, then hoped? True Chriſtians eſpecially being the obiects of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and fury of the world; ſecondly, peace amongſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:156:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>our ſelues. As when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſayth vnto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.51. haue ſalt in your ſelues, and be at peace one with another. But amongſt ſuch varietie of humaine paſſions, and ſo many civill broyles, what ſalt, what wiſedome will ſuffice to ſeaſon it, if the bond of the ſpirit and true Chriſtianitie come not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene? for even amongſt the Apoſtles themſelues at the evening of the Paſſion, and in the preſence of their maiſter, yea even of ſuch a maiſter, who ſaw the very depth of their ſoules, what diſputes had they? And now laſt of all, peace amongſt our ſelues. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Apoſtle exhorteth
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:156:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Be at peace among your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that is to ſay, poſſeſſe your ſoules in patience. But againe, how can this be, where the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man ſtriveth againſt the inward, the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, the ſpirit of fleſh, againſt the ſpirit of God, the law of our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, againſt the law of our minde, tameth it, leadeth it captiue, is ſold vnder ſinne? But in that peace which we haue with God by Chriſt alone, wee recover all this, even peace with all men, will they, nill they. Becauſe he who hath peace with the Creator, hath it with the Creature, with the whole order of nature, with his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies celeſtiall &amp; terreſtiall,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:156:64"/>ſeeing all depend vpon his pay, taketh the watch word from him, who guideth their blowes, and directs them, as it pleaſeth him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would ſeeme vnto thee mortall, to be for thy health, and for thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Peace with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for he bridleth the Sea, moderateth the fire, ſo as he who lodgeth vnder the ſhaddow of the Almightie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.</note> needes not feare any thing which terrifieth by night, or flyeth in the day, which deſtroyeth at noone tyde. Peace with the beaſts of the field; for he muzzells the mouth of the hungrie Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Out of the eater he giues meate, and out of the ſtrong he bringeth forth ſweetneſſe.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:156:64"/>Iudg.</hi> 14.14. Peace with men, though worſe one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Lyons, for ſayth the Prophet. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 56. God is on my ſide, what then can man or fleſh doe vnto mee? Peace with death. <hi>Pſal.</hi> the 3. ſo that although thouſands ſhould ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle array againſt mee, I ſhould not ſleepe a whit the worſe, becauſe he is on my ſide. Peace with the graue, and with hell; for is it not he, that bringeth to the graue, and rayſeth vs vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? and what can death bring vnto mee but life? Death which is but for a moment; life eternall. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. the 54.55. <hi>Death is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp into victory.</hi> Our Lord Ieſus, hath not he tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:156:65"/>for vs? <hi>O death, where is thy victory?</hi> Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth where are thy triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phs? <hi>Hell, where is thy ſting?</hi> The power of ſinne being now aboliſhed by grace? And therefore wee haue peace with all, ſeing al their might and weapons turne to our peace, all their curſes into bleſſings, all their gaſhes, how terrible ſoever they may be, are turned into balme, their tempeſts into ſafe havens. All theſe things I ſay, and all others what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, worke together, as ſayth the Apoſtle, vnto our good, and that becauſe of the loue of God, which is purchaſed for vs by Ieſus Chriſt; for in ſteade of a judge, he is now become a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:156:65"/>father, and of a iuſt reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a gracious protector, diſpoſing all againſt the haire to our victory, to our peace, to our glory and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Peace alſo amongſt our ſelues; with our brethren, though ſome be hardly and not eaſily to be reconciled, yet when we come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what and how many offences God hath forgiven vs, and doth alſo daily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs; even that God, who is judge &amp; ſoveraigne Lord of all the world, not ſparing his owne Sonne, for the ranſome of our ſins; what offence then ought there to be ſo grievous vnto vs, that ſhould make vs to beare malice in our hearts
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:156:66"/>againſt our brother? or what pardon ſhould ſeeme hard or difficult vnto vs, be it to require, be it to graunt, to keepe backe, or recover friendſhip with them? But there is yet more, for will they, nill they, thou haſt peace with them, though it be wanting on their part whilſt thou giueſt not place to wrath, whilſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceſt revenge, in doing good for evill. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20. When thou holdeſt thy ſelfe for revenged, by doing them good. A glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and of a high ſtraine, farre more glorious then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other; for ther by though they make not vſe of it, thou heapeſt coales of fire vpon their heads. And ſuch was
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:156:66"/>that peace which <hi>David;</hi> that valourous Prince had, who overcame a Lyon with his ſtrength, a <hi>Goliah</hi> by his proweſſe, who had both gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and alſo wonne ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny battayles, who faſted and put on ſackcloth for his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, who in the middeſt of the ruine which they plotted againſt him, begged of God their life, &amp; having them in his full power, was contented with the skirt of his garment. <hi>Lord,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>if I haue not kept him who wrongfully oppreſſed mee, let the Enemie purſue mee, and take me, let him treade my life vpon the ground, and lay my honor in the duſt.</hi> Pſal. 7. A true figure of him, who here leaues vnto vs his peace,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:156:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>and yet more liuely in his owne example, who prayed for thoſe that crucified him, and was crucified for them that offended him. This Philoſophy, nay rather Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, how farre remote is it from that of the world? Moreover, he tells vs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that hee leaveth it not vnto vs, <hi>as the world doth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>peace</hi> in our ſelues; behold the principal peace; for in vaine will it be for vs, to haue peace without vs, if wee haue warre within vs, health in the Cittie, if the Plague be in our boſome, if our conſcience accuſe vs, if our ſinnes warre againſt vs? But is it poſſible to ſmoother ſin in our ſelues? Let vs if we can. But who
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:156:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>can doe it, and who is it that doth not every houre kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it? Yea rather giue fire as it were vnto it? We would faine ſtill the ſting of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Alas! the remedie is worſe then the diſeaſe; What will it be but a gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene in ſtead of an vlcer? Let vs then imbrace that grace, which God offereth vnto vs in Ieſus Chriſt by a liuely faith. Let vs awaken our Conſcience to find out her ſinnes, to ſearch her wounds to the bottome, being aſſured, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing them, it ſhall beſayd vnto vs, goe in peace, and in laying them open, it ſhall become our healing; And which is more, wee ſhall be ſtrengthened in ſpirit to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:156:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>wreſtle againſt fleſh and bloud, againſt all ſpirituall powers and wickedneſſes; ſo that the fleſh ſtriving within vs againſt the ſpirit, wee may notwithſtanding ſay with the Apoſtle. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>In that I liue now in the fleſh, I liue yet by the faith of the Sonne of God, who hath loved me, and given himſelfe for mee.</hi> Though I fight, and the Combat be ſharpe, yet the quarrell is juſt, and the iſſue certaine. <hi>I haue kept the faith,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Paul, therefore the Crowne of righteouſneſſe is layd vp for me.</hi> 2 Tim. 4.8. <hi>Theſe things haue I ſayd vnto you,</hi> ſayth our Lord vnto his Apoſtles, <hi>that you might haue peace in mee, in the world you ſhall haue affliction;</hi> yea he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:156:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>foretold them of all ſorts of afflictions. Whence then is this peace? He addeth, but be of good courage, <hi>I haue overcome the world;</hi> and am now about to giue it the laſt deadly blow; for you principally; as for my ſelfe, it is alreadie overcome; the victory is yours, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines for you perfect peace, that is, your reconciliation with God, and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thereof, a freedome from all perills and feare; <hi>For if whilſt we were enemies</hi> (there being nothing in vs, nor ought that could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from vs, which did not provoke his anger) <hi>wee were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>being now reconciled,</hi> his good favour
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:156:69"/>being reſtored againe vnto vs, <hi>ſhall wee not then much more be ſaved by his life?</hi> He living in vs, raigning for vs, who vouchſafed to dye for vs? Is not the Kingdome of God within vs? to wit, <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>peace and ioy.</hi> Rom. 14.17.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle amongſt the fruits of the ſpirit of Chriſt dwelling in vs, ſets downe firſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> the 5.21. <hi>Ioy, peace, mecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Being now priſoner at <hi>Rome;</hi> where they are wont to be impatient; or where commonly they find neither ioy, nor peace; yet he tells vs that his bonds in Chriſt, did confirme his brethren <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.14. that he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:156:69"/>reioyceth to be offered vpon the ſervice of the faith of the <hi>Philippians;</hi> &amp; prayeth them to reioyce with him; But how? even by the vertue of this <hi>peace of God,</hi> Phil. 4.7. <hi>which paſſeth all vndo ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and keepeth our beaies and mindes in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> which conſequently ought <hi>to hold the chiefe place in our hearts,</hi> to ſubdue all other affections, with all other paſſions. <hi>Collo.</hi> 3.15. Such peace as proceedeth from the loue of God, ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in our ſoules, ſuch a loue which hath his roote in that reconciliation, made onely by the death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt; wherein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guiltie, wee are abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; of ſinners, made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:156:70"/> of enemies, familiar friends; of ſervants, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, redeemed by the death of that well beloved Sonne, by whoſe ſpirit wee cry, <hi>Abba Father.</hi> And here ô Chriſtian remember, each one in his Calling, how many Combats, how many perplexities thou meeteſt with? Publicke, private, without, within, corporall, and ſpirituall; and in the middeſt of the ſtrongeſt of them, yet holding tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; poſſeſſing the peace of thy ſoule. From whence hadſt thou this, but from this onely peace of God, which alone can pacific the torments of the ſoule? On the contrary, O thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wretch, how many
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:156:70"/>times even in the height of thy proſperities, and in thy ſafeſt and ſureſt haven, haſt thou found reſt to thy ſoul? And why? onely becauſe the Lord ſayth by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.19.20. that vnto them <hi>which mourne, I giue conſolations, peace, yea, even peace vnto him that is neere, and to him that is farre off.</hi> I willingly draw neere vnto them, though they ſeeme never ſo farre off. But <hi>the wicked,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>are like vnto a troubled Sea, which cannot be appeaſed, her waues caſt vp myre and durt.</hi> The Sea, which when all winds be ſtill, yet is mooved by his owne proper motion. So the wicked hath his owne heart vexing him, and in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:156:71"/>the height of his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſuſters him not to bee quiet.</p>
            <p>Alſo, he by and by addes, I giue not vnto you <hi>my peace as the world giveth it;</hi> The world giveth that which is outward, but I my ſelfe, that which is inward; The world giueth it you, in your fields, in your vineyards, and in your gardens; but I giue it you in your ſoules. Now that peace which the world giues, it giues it by with-holding; now to giue, and yet to keepe backe, is vſually of no eſteeme. But I giue it you without ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, without grudging ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely; abſolute, even for ever and ever. But peace commonly amongſt men is
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:156:71"/>onely held by ſome recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call intereſt, or vnder a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall feare; where ſomewhat is wanting on either ſide; and therefore ſoone diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. But that peace which I giue you, is not ſubiect to ſuch accidents; yee haue it altogether from me, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freely; what can all of you giue vnto mee? poore ſilly Creatures; Am not I the living God, what can I looke for from you? Where of ſhould I be afraid? This then is the peace, which our Lord Ieſus leaveth here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Apoſtles, vnto his Diſciples; and vnto all thoſe which haue beleeved their word. Peace with God; peace in their Conſciences; for as much as <hi>the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:156:72"/>of the father was to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile vs vnto himſelfe, and to make this peace by the bloud of the Croſſe of his Sonne.</hi> Truely his <hi>good pleaſure, Coloſſ.</hi> 1.10. for, whence elſe could it be expected? Peace, which diſchargeth vs of our ſinnes, in as much as hee beareth them, and clotheth vs with his righteouſneſſe. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. for as much as wee are made <hi>the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in him.</hi> Peace, which delivers vs from the evill of the fault, in as much as it is forgiven vs; from the evill of puniſhment, becauſe they turne to our good; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying our Conſciences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his anger; In as much as of enemies we are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into his favour, our
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:156:72"/>ſoules partakers of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in as much as wee are incorporated not onely into his alliance, but alſo into his familie; In him, I ſay, <hi>who of God, is made vnto vs, wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and redemption.</hi> To whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be glory for ever and ever.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:73"/>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:156:73"/>
            <head>AN HOMILIE VPON THESE WORDS;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>One thing is needfull.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke. 10.41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo Siſters receiue our LORD into their houſe; to wit, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> And <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> makes her Complaint vnto him, that whilſt ſhee was buſie to giue him good entertainment, <hi>Mary</hi> her
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:156:74"/>ſiſter ſits downe at his feete to heare his Preaching, not caring to put to her helping hand: whereunto our Lord anſweres, <hi>Martha, Martha,</hi> (which name twice repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, advertiſeth her to take the greater heede to that he had to ſay vnto her) <hi>thou art troubled about many things, but one thing is neceſſary;</hi> not reproving her for the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of loue ſhee went about, being ſuch as were both ſeemely and commendable, and where I pray you could they be better beſtowed, then vpon our Lord? But our Saviour recalleth her vnto a more principall, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and onely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worke; being a thing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall with the ſonne of God
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:156:74"/>(who deſcended from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to lift vs vp thither) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to weane vs from too much minding our belly; our worke; and to draw vs from this earthly life, vnto the heavenly; from theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior and humane offices, vnto thoſe benefits, which bring vs vnto the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Manſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One thing</hi> then ſayth he, even one thing <hi>is neceſſary;</hi> To the meaner ſort, how many things ſeeme neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? To thoſe of higher ranke, many things are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; vnto the wiſe, many things paſſe from pleaſant, vnto things profitable, from profitable to things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and even amongſt theſe neceſſary things, how
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:156:75"/>many of them are choſen, or refuſed? and yet Lord thou ſayſt, that one thing onely is neceſſary; thou who being man, converſeſt amongſt men, couldeſt not be ignorant, that in a houſe, where there are a number of imployments, if but one thing be wanting, we think we are halfe, if not wholly maymed; In like manner, in a ſtore-houſe, after wee haue imagined, whatſoever can be deviſed, yet many things are ſtill wanting. Thou, O God and man in one perſon; who didſt giue thine aſſiſtance at the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things; thou haſt made an infinite number of things, as the Elements, Mineralls, Plants, living
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:156:75"/>Creatures, Planets, Starres, and all for the vſe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of men; nay rather of one man. And yet thou here telleſt vs, That <hi>One thing is neceſſary;</hi> what then? are all other things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuperfluous! Hath na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture made ought in vaine? or thou LORD ſo many things in vaine? As though thou wert leſſe then thy Creature. What then would become of that <hi>manifolde wiſedome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that wiſedome of thine, who tookeſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to create varietie of things? Varietie then, not vanitie, ſeeing it came from, and alſo depends on thy wiſedome. And therefore let vs waigh this ſaying of our Lord, who contradicts
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:156:76"/>not himſelfe, either in words, or actions, and let vs ſeeke with reverence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many things, what then may be this <hi>One thing neceſſary.</hi> The which certainely ought to glad vs, and to giue worth to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One thing</hi> then ſayth he, <hi>is neceſſary;</hi> neceſſary for thee <hi>Martha,</hi> and vnto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beleever: Now we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly account that neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with which wee can, and without the which wee cannot liue, much leſſe liue well; wee I ſay, who are compoſed of body &amp; ſoule, one part mortall, the other immortall. It ſhould then follow, that this one thing
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:156:76"/>muſt haue reference vnto both, otherwiſe, one thing would not ſuffice both, but one of them rather then the other, rather the ſoule then the bodie, according to the vſuall manner of Chriſtes words, which alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the ſoule more then the bodie, not as having an eye vnto the bodie; but for the good of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs ſtand no longer Cheapening about riches, favours, greatneſſe, health, or knowledg; things which are not heere to be ſought for, nor in this one thing to be found; things which all men haue not; for if all were rich, mightie, learned, then there ſhould be no difference at all. Men
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:156:77"/>being reſpected more or leſſe, according as they want theſe things, or as they haue them in greater abundance then others. Our Lord then, to giue it vs in one word, ſayth, that <hi>Mary hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not be taken from her;</hi> For, for the moſt part, thoſe things formerly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, are ſubiect to periſh, and totally to be loſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this one thing muſt needes be <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> that is, mans dutie towardes God, and his well-being with God, ſubſiſting in it ſelfe, without the ayde or helpe of any other, having the promiſes both of things preſent and to come, which onely giveth the forme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:156:77"/>all thoſe other thinges: Without this, being but a confuſed lumpe, whether mixed therewith, or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent, making them either good or evill, as the ſalt to ſeaſon them, which otherwiſe would putrefie and corrupt: or as the ſoule; giving them their life, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and motion, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would turne and paſſe into rottenneſſe, into wormes, and into ſerpents; which being ingendered therein, eate out the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells. And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> concludes with vs, who had taſted of them, even to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte, and poſſeſſed them to his fill; <hi>Vanitie,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>Eccl.</hi> the 1. <hi>and all is vanitie. Feare God,</hi> then ſayth he,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:156:78"/>
               <hi>and keepe his Comandements; for this is the whole dutie of man.</hi> Eccl. 12. This our Lord (a greater then <hi>Salomon</hi>) tells vs, is that <hi>One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi> For doe we not ſee that our firſt Father in his integritie, the Monarch of all the world, not keeping himſelfe vnto <hi>this one thing,</hi> but ſuffering himſelfe to be deprived of his favour, which preſerved him, and made him better then all things; thereby loſt the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and almoſt the vſe and knowledge of them; ſo as notwithſtanding the whole world was created for him, yet hee revolting, all became accurſed and damnable vnto him, from the greateſt of the creatures
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:156:78"/>even to the leaſt. The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments turned into corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the beaſts of the earth into rebellion, the creeping things vnto perſecution, the hearbs into poyſon, the corne into thornes. A curſe which cannot be repayred, but by returning vnto this onely <hi>pietie,</hi> which by the perſwaſion of Sathan, hee loſt for all his poſteritie, but is now found againe for thoſe who cleaue vnto God, in our ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> to wit, in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, God and man, who ſets vs againe in our way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, making peace betweene him and vs; And therefore he prayſeth <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who keepes neere vnto him, ſitting at his feete,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:156:79"/>who ſetting aſide all other buſineſſe in the houſe, lets not goe her hold, becauſe in him ſhee finds all things, or rather forgets all other things, who indeed ſucked the doctrine of life from that mouth, and from that ſacred ſpring; and on the contrary, hee reformeth <hi>Martha,</hi> and cals her away, from her houſhold affaires, and civill complements to a dutie of an higher nature, wherein are to be found and recovered all other things, that is vnto the ſtudie of pietie, and vnto <hi>this onely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary thing, Iacobs</hi> portion, <hi>Maries</hi> lot, even that pearle for the attaining whereof, all muſt be ſould, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45. which thing being once
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:156:79"/>got, <hi>can never be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Chriſtian, art thou rich, glory not therein; but be thou poore, and be thou humble in ſpirit, thinke that theſe riches are given vnto thee, to make tryall of thy liberalitie towardes the Saints, and of thy charitie towardes thy neighbours; and ſo they turne as a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto thee, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe are to thee a ſnare, the cauſe of a heavie recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, reſerving to him a great remaynder to be payd downe preſently, or elſe to priſon, or rather to the rack. But art thou poore, &amp; waſt thou ſo borne; thinke thou then, that God in his juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, hath neede of ſergeants
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:156:80"/>and officers, to Cite and Summon the rich. Or art thou decayd by theeues, fire, or by ſome banckrupt; thinke then, that thereby God hath diſcharged thee of this great account, and therewithall hath lightened thine expences from ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, vnto which theſe riches might ſeeme to bind thee; and ſo to bring thee to that eſtate, he hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for thee. But is it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous vnto thee, to haue loſt that which once thou hadſt, yea more grievous, then if thou hadſt never had it; thinke that in ſtead of being able to relieue others, God calls thee to faith; thinke alſo,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that GOD hath his Champions, his Actors,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:156:80"/>and ſo will haue thee to be one of them, and that hee vnclothes when and whom it pleaſeth him, to ſet them (as it were) vpon the ſtage naked as my nayle, even to the waſt; having neither raiment nor weapons to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend themſelues withall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the iniury of the weather, nor againſt the gripes of the world, but onely his<note n="*" place="margin">Alluding to that oyle w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vſed to annoint themſelues with, being naked from the girdle vpward.</note> Oyle. But if they were clothed like others, be it as rich as might be, yet were they not acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Champions, but if they come vpon the ſtage naked; the beholders are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue; they looke, they admire their armes, their ſinewes, their ligaments, their muſckles, the ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:156:81"/> of their ſtanding, the force of their gripes: their faith, their conſtancie, their vertue, or rather the ſtrength of this holy oyle of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, which is in them. And being ready to depart thence, they are proclaimed by the Herauld, they carrie away the prize, the crowne which withereth not. Seeſt thou not then, how pietie ſeaſoneth the evill of thy povertie, or wouldſt thou now rather haue had the faireſt garment of the rich?</p>
            <p>Art thou in credit or repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? thinke it is but a ſmoake of the Court; and beware leaſt it turne to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Art thou as a <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> pray for thy Lord and Maiſter; Be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:156:81"/>vnto his people, forget not thy thy kindred, nor familie; whether within or without; in the Church, or in the Common-weale, but according to thy power, as a feeling member thereof, make them ſenſible of thy fidelity. But art thou none of theſe, but one of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort, it may be, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou deſerveſt not better, then thinke with thy ſelfe; that he who diſpoſeth all thinges with waight, number, and meaſure, who diſcerneth within thee, that thou ſeeſt not thy ſelfe; knowes beſt what is fitteſt for thee; handles thee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy diſpoſition, hee takes that wine from thee, which heated thy liver, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:156:82"/>therefore brought thee to this dyet. And therefore bridle thine appetite, and looke vpon his favours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repining, liue without envie. But haſt thou beene in credite and reputation, and art thou reiected, be it by alteration of thine eſtate, or by the Prince, not of thy ſelfe, be not diſcouraged, thy fall is not great, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou canſt be no more reverenced vpon thy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot as a <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence thee as a <hi>Iob,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vpon a dunghill, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by thoſe holy conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which thou haſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hereby thy ſelfe, and which thou ſhalt alſo leaue vnto others. Beleeue mee,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:156:82"/>that all thoſe applaudings, thoſe flatteries, thoſe adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which were given vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> are now vaniſhed in the ayre, who nouriſhed ſo many bodies, and ſaved them from famine; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the contrary, the holy ſpeeches of <hi>Iob,</hi> are conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated vnto all eternitie for inſtruction, and are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perpetuall conſolations, reviveth and comforteth the ſoules of the Saints vnto this day; and then, this danghill being ordered by pietie, wouldſt thou change it for the ſmokes of a Court, or for all the glory and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Aegypt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou a Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">A Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note> thinke then with thy ſelfe, that he who judgeth here
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:156:83"/>below, ſhall be thy ludge from aboue, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo that thou executeſt Gods judgement, and not thine. And therefore exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute judgement and juſtice; juſtice in helping the poore out of oppreſſion, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in chaſtizing the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, without exception, without acception of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And hold godlineſſe alwayes as thy ſword in thy right hand, poyſe thy bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance ſtraight, not to make a falſe draught, but to carry it even.</p>
            <p>But art thou a private perſon,<note place="margin">A private perſon</note> thinke then how much GOD hath ſpared thee, who haſt not to giue account of the goods of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, nor of the bloud of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:156:83"/>thy brethren. Arme thy ſelfe to ſuffer iniuries, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in thy minde, in thine owne conſcience, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between ſuch an high eſtate, and thy meane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whether in ſuffering or doing.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou beene a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke perſon,<note place="margin">Of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke perſon beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming a private.</note> and art thou now deprived; deprived, not having deſerved it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived peradventure having deſerved better, and more then deſerved it alſo; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed notwithſtanding of ſcarlet, &amp; brought to weare freeſe; then thinke with thy ſelfe, how often thou haſt willingly vnclothed thee, to go to bed, and didſt thou ſleepe the worſe, to take thine eaſe? thinke then
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:156:84"/>with thy ſelfe, that this coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attyre, is ſuch where the Mothe moſt breeds, the Mothe of the Court; as jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, ſlander, envie. But rather remember how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kings and Emperours, being weary of wearing their Crownes, impatient of ſuſtaining and vndergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, haue caſt them off, deteſted them, to finde reſt vnto their minde, and that by laying them aſide. Many alſo to ſeek the health of their ſoules, which they thought could not ſtand therewith, namely, true pie tie, this <hi>One thing neceſſary;</hi> and yet pietie, which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres neither Scepters nor Crownes, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, makes them flouriſh,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:156:84"/>when they beleeue it. But to a very few hath the Lord vſually given, eſpecially, to theſe great powers, a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie to holde them vpon ſuch dependences. And from thence comes ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſeries in the world.</p>
            <p>But beſides, be it thou be diſrobed, and further vexed in thy eſtate; they grate thee, they hewe thee; know how that God hath his dimonds amongſt men; and we are beautifull, if we be ſuch. Rough as they be, he puties them vnder the Wheele of ſteele; he poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them, he ſmoothes them, he cuts them in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in pomted ones, &amp;c. Otherwiſe, it could not be done; and then they ſhew
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:156:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>their hardneſſe, their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their fire; their faith; their ſinceritie, their zeale. And therefore feare not that he who is ſo good a lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eller, ſhould marre thee; for in cutting away ſome of thy rubbiſh,<note place="margin">Note.</note> he giues thee thy forme; by diminiſhing of thy waight, he augments thy price. Pretie teacheth it thee, it telles thee, that <hi>all things</hi> (nothing excepted) <hi>worke together for good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 8.28</note> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping forward the ſalvation <hi>of them that loue it;</hi> but to ſpeake it more warily, <hi>to thoſe that it loues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of an helth full conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of body.</note>Art thou healthfull, art thou ſtrong, it is a gift of God; giue him thankes for it, but abuſe it not vnto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and violence, poſſeſſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:156:85"/>theſe, as things that are but frayle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of a ſickly conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>But art thou ſickly, and afflicted with infirmities, and hath Sathan touched thy fleſh? afflict not thy ſelfe aboue meaſure; thinke that theſe grieſes, are as ſo many ſummons, and goads, to vrge thee to pray vnto God, to call for his grace; nay rather, prayſe him.<note place="margin">Note.</note> How often are the ſickneſſes of the body ſent, for the health of the ſoule, and haue kept vs from ſinnes and other follies? For ſickneſſes, and adverſities; haue their ſongs of prayſe, no leſſe then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities, yea even as well as the greateſt joyes; in their divers accents, and tunes of ſweetneſſe, moſt harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:156:86"/>we haue an example in <hi>David,</hi> who ſung more in affliction, then when he was jocund; yea even in adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee ſeemes to redouble his melodie; becauſe our nature being little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſenſible of the graces of God, is not touched vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the quicke; hath quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough, or lightly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it over, and according as his hand is light or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, it leapeth, it cryeth, and will haue no nay, vntill ſhe be heard.<note place="margin">Note.</note> But know be ſides, O Chriſtian, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hath her part to pl y, as well as joyes; that as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath emptineſſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding it in order, ſo ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hath her ſweete reliſh, which ſtirres thee vp to call
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:156:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon thy Creator in thy miſery, and heareſt him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering thee by his holy ſpirit in his mercy, who feeleſt him in thy ſoule from his ſweete hand, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a ſlumber vpon thy ſorrowes; binding vp thy ſoares; who teaching thee, cauſeth thee to ſee that they are but inciſſions of the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and not the wounds of an enemy, being guided by the judgement of loue, and not by a fury of hatred. Whence the Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. <hi>To reioyce alwayes in the Lord, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to reioyce,</hi> being in a ſeaſon, when the Apoſtle was full of combatts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and of Bondes, himſelfe being bound for
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:156:87"/>the Goſpell; But obſerue, that he ſayth, <hi>in the Lord;</hi> for as much as pietie makes vs receiue it all from God, and as from a father, makes vs to take ſickneſſes, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the body as a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation for the health of the ſoule; for as much as but one dramme of the loue of God manifeſted vnto vs by his ſpirit, is of power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue a ſea of griefes; there needing but one ſparke of the ſpirit of God, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of ſuch as are learned.</note>In a word, art thou lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I will further inſtruct thee, for know thou, that whatſoever thou knoweſt, is not the thouſand part, of that whereof thou artigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; for he who was moſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:156:87"/>expert in the knowledge of the matters of this life, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that all his knowledge was but vanitie; yea vanity more apt to puffe vp, then to fill; to make thee proud, rather then truely glorious.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A learned ignorance.</note>There is alſo a certaine learned ignorance, that one who is truly learned, would preferre before all thy lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; And therefore in prayſing God for his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, referring them to their right end, namely, vnto pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to the ſervice of God, without the which they are nothing: be not then I pray thee, too wiſe in thy ſelfe. But art thou ignorant,<note place="margin">Of ſuch as are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> or eſteemeſt thou thy ſelfe to be ſo; who dareſt not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:156:88"/>ſpeake before others, and art aſhamed of thy ſelfe. Be not therefore troubled; I am about to teach thee how to be both better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and wiſe; if thou wilt beleeue me, nay, if thou wilt but beleeue even that great learned Apoſtle, who 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. determined among his <hi>Corinthians, to know nothing, but Ieſus Chriſt, and him Crucified,</hi> was notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rapt vp into the third heaven, into Paradice, where he both heard and ſawe, things not to be vttered, and yet of all that, he makes no reckoning, in reſpect of this onely knowledge, the knowledg of this one thing, which is <hi>onely neceſſary,</hi> on which they are all either
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:156:88"/>grounded, or confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſee then how pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuffers not riches to make vs proud; nor to turne favour into oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, greatneſſe into vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, health into diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, knowledge into vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but extracting theſe from it, as it were poyſon from Vipers; to make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of good Treacle, turning it into the medicine of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſocietie, being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, both dangerous and deadly to meddle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. It ſupplies alſo all our wants, poverties, infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, afflictions, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, as onely neceſſarie, like vnto that hearbe <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco,</hi> ſo much extolled in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:156:89"/>the New-found-Landes, which alone is ſufficient for meate and drinke, for Clothes, and for Phyſicke. Wee ſay, like to that <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> in the Wilderneſſe (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Iewiſh <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi>) which fitted every mans taſte, whatſoever he deſired, elſe were there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little of this drugge, it would convert to it ſelfe, and into it ſelfe, every other thing.</p>
            <p>See another Example in Saint <hi>Paul. Phil.</hi> 4. ver. 11. <hi>I haue learned,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>to be content with that I haue, I know how to want, and how to abound, every where, and in all things, I am taught, as well to be ſatisfied, as to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as well to abound, as to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:156:89"/>want.</hi> But heare how? <hi>I am able to performe all things in Chriſt, who giues me ſtrength,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> in and by this his onely grace. This onely grace of Chriſt doth furniſh all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apt onely of it ſelfe, both to pare away our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and to ſupply our wantes, to make vs finde contentment in povertie, and glory in ſhame. And therefore ſayth he elſwhere; <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory in any thing, but in the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> A poore glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wilt thou ſay, in one Crucified; He is dead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but is riſen againe, aſcended into heaven, and raigneth there. Of which glory, of which kingdome, hee that is a member of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:156:90"/>Chriſt, feeles himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie partaker of. Who thinketh it ſtrange, that the head being in heaven, the feete ſhould not haue a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling therewith, ſhould not glory therewith, though creeping here belowe on the earth. And from this glory it commeth, that the Apoſtle ſtiles himſelfe, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it in the front of one of his Epiſtles. <hi>Philem.</hi> 1. <hi>Paul a priſoner of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in bondes for his Name. Might hee not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (wilt thou ſay) haue ſtiled himſelfe with a more honourable title, namely, Rapt vp into Paradiſe, as if he had beene equall to the Angells.<note place="margin">Note.</note> But his pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, this faith in Chriſt,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:156:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>honours him, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his bondes; ſo that to ſuffer in Earth for Chriſt, is more vnto him, then to be taken vp into heaven, this raviſhment being of ſhort continuance, but his ſufferings which aſſure him of his promiſe, to haue there an everlaſting being, and to raigne there for ever with him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is meant by this one thing.</note>But heere O Chriſtian, it may be thou deſireſt to knowe, wherein <hi>this one thing,</hi> properly conſiſtes, which hath ſo many ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and onely can doe all things, but thinkeſt, and feareſt, that this knowledge is too laborious, who ſeeſt ſo many bookes of ſo long ſtudies written, ſo many
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:156:91"/>degrees to paſſe through, to attaine to ſo high a knowledge. And verily, the myſtery of godlineſſe is great, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>That God was manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentiles, beleeved on in the world, and received vp into glory.</hi> For of every one of theſe Articles, there might Volumes be made. The Angels themſelues, ſayth Saint <hi>Peter, deſire to prie thereinto.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.12. But for all this be not diſmayd. For God the Creator of man in his mercies, would that this myſtery ſhould of right belong as well vnto the ignorant, as vnto the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:156:91"/>learned; by very Idiottes he hath converted Orators; in the netts of poore Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, he hath taken Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers; In one and the ſame Sea, both great and ſmall fiſh liue and ſwimme; depths for the one, and ſhallowneſſe for the other; thou haſt thy part in this myſtery, or rather thy pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, though thou coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not reade. Vnder the Law it was ſayd, <hi>doe this,</hi> fulfill the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, <hi>and thou ſhalt liue;</hi> A leſſon propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned according to that integritie, wherein our firſt parents were created. After ſo great a fall, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>placed, which bruiſed all
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:156:92"/>his faculties, and ours in him; as over-matched. For where is the man that ever did, or could performe it? But Chriſt our Lord by his perfect obedience, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent onely to ſatisfie for vs, but therewithall giues vs a leſſon, both ſhorter and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, that is, this myſtery of faith; <hi>If thou confeſſe,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle, <hi>the Lord Ieſus with thy mouth, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt in thy heart, that GOD hath rayſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved. Rom.</hi> 10.9. Wilt thou haue it in other words; <hi>Theſe things are written,</hi> ſayth S. <hi>Iohn;</hi> theſe Goſpels. <hi>Ioh.</hi> the 20. and laſt verſe, <hi>that thou mightst beleeue, that Ieſus is
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:156:92"/>the Chriſt, the ſonne of God, and that in beleeving, you might haue life in his Name.</hi> And wilt thou make it thine, and appropriate it vnto thy ſelfe, ſay then, with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>It is a true ſaying, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of all acceptation,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore waver not, neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, but with him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whom</hi> ſay thou, <hi>I am chiefe.</hi> Here thou haſt thy part, take it home vnto thee, it is <hi>Maries</hi> part, <hi>which cannot be taken from her.</hi> Cleaue therefore vnto Chriſt, and caſt downe at his feete (by her example) the pride of thy fleſh, the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:156:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>opinion of thy owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, make thee a ſeat at his feete, by humilitie, in ſeeking his favour, which is thy reconciliation with the Father; And then ſay thou, but not as <hi>David, thy Law</hi> O Lord;<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.98</note> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>thy Goſpell,</hi> which is the end of the Law; <hi>Faith in thy Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 10.4.</note> hath made mee more learned and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, then all the learned men in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Faith, if of the right ſtamp, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiue.</note>But learne alſo, that this faith is not an emptie, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary, or idle opinion, but an inward and found per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, which hath a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which manifeſts it ſelfe by workes, makes a deepe Impreſſion in thy
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:156:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoule, engraues Chriſt in thy heart, in thy ſpirit; begetting in thine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a feeling of the loue of God towards thee, in thy will a holy fire of loue towardes God, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the ſame his loue, which quencheth in thee all other loues,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth not thereon; but aboue all, the loue of thy ſelfe. And therefore even as when thou haſt grafted a grift vpon a wilde ſtocke, and a while after commeſt to ſee, if it hath taken; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt the barke greene, ſome budds; and a little after, both leaues and fruit, thou reioyceſt and holdeſt it as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nne; ſo in like manner
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:156:94"/>wilt thou ſee, if the ſaith of Chriſt be rooted in thee; and that vnto ſalvation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view thy ſelfe from time to time, if it hath imprinted in thee a hunger after the knowledge of God, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſire to pleaſe him, a feare to offend him, to order thy ſences, thy moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, thy actions, thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to governe the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both of body and ſoule, as inſtruments of puritie, of integritie, of charitie, of juſtice, to renew thee from day to day, in thy inward and outward man, caſting forth a good ſavour in thy life, and converſation, then ſay boldly, that faith hath taken roote in thee, and the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:156:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>gift is paſt the worſt: but aboue all, if ſhee renounce her firſt ſape, to receiue it from Chriſt; this grafting being of another nature then ours are, becauſe theſe turne the wilde ſape into them, contrarily, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyeth vs to Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts vs into Chriſt, whence wee may then ſay with S. <hi>Paul, Galat.</hi> 2. and 20. <hi>I liue, yet not I, but Christ liues in mee, and whilſt I liue now in the fleſh, I liue in the faith of the Sonne of God, who hath loved mee, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven himſelfe for mee.</hi> Being readie to caſt away what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in vs, and of vs, whatſoever ſeemes to be moſt precious in our eye;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:156:95"/>to keepe, and to preſerue this onely; even this one onely <hi>neceſſary thing,</hi> which is worth them all; being then every way fit to ſay vnto Chriſt, with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and boldneſſe; I haue ſinned, but I know that thou art my JESVS, the Sonne of God my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, this onely word ſufficeth; let vs therefore keepe it pure, and without mixture, with this Word let vs paſſe the night of this world, let vs paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Barricadoes, and Watches; if we meete with ſome rubbes, though it be with ſome danger, yet let vs goe forward till breake of day, even of our day,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:156:95"/>of our reſt, there wee ſhall ſee our IESVS raigning in heaven, to liue with him, where wee ſhall raigne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, glorifying him for ever; to whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit be glory for ever, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:156:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156:96"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 112. line 21. and 113. l. 2. for <hi>amongst,</hi> read <hi>in.</hi> P. 136. l. 5. for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeſt,</hi> read <hi>converſedſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
